斯坦福大学
Stanford University.
欢迎来到CS193P课程 2013-14秋季第12讲
Okay, well welcome to CS193p, Lecture 12 of fall 2013 and 14,
今天我们只有一个主题 也就是Core Data
and today we have one topic and one topic only, which is core data.
之前有人问过 第五次作业周三交
And, as someone was asking earlier, assignment 5 is due on Wednesday
而最后一次作业 作业六 到时也会布置 一周后交
and then your last assignment, assignment 6, will go out then and be due a week later.
周三 我将讲到期末项目要求
On Wednesday, I'm going to be going over the final project requirements
我们还会继续讲一点Core Data
and we're going to continue with core data a little bit,
讨论Core Data和UITableView
talk about core data with table, UI table view.
然后我要做一个大的演示
And then I'm going to do a big demo.
今天的课将都是幻灯片讲解
So today's lecture is going to be all slides.
一般我不喜欢这样做 一次讲太多幻灯片并不好
I don't usually like to do that just because it's an awful lot of slides all at once,
不过这次我打算这样做
but it makes sense in this case
今天内容的演示都将放到周三
and I'll be doing the demo for today's stuff on Wednesday,
然后下周 我们会谈到高级segue
and then next week we'll start talking about advanced segueing
或许我们还会讨论MapKit 多任务处理
and maybe we'll do some map kit, multitasking,
下周会讲什么我不确定
I'm not quite sure what I'm going to cover next week
因为这方面 你们将没有作业
because you won't have a homework assignment on that.
今天和周三我要讲的Core Data内容
This core data stuff that we're covering today and Wednesday,
将是你们最后一次作业的主题
that's going to be the topic of your last homework assignment
这次作业将在周三布置
that goes out on Wednesday.
Core Data 什么是Core Data
So, core data, what is core data?
Core Data是一个面向对象的数据库
Core data is an object-oriented database.
我们为什么需要它呢
Why do we need it?
原因在于 在大型应用程序中
Because in any kind of significant application
我们需要处理很多数据
where we have a lot of data to crunch on,
我们不能将其存储于NSUserDefault或是完全不存储
we can't be storing it in NS user defaults or not storing it at all,
完全从Flickr上进行下载 对吧
or always fetching it down from Flickr, right?
你们当前的作业 以及上周的Shutterbug演示
So your current assignment, or the Shutterbug demo that we did last week,
我们一直是在取回整个模型
we're just always fetching our entire model,
每次都要从Flickr取回
basically, every time we want it from Flickr,
但如果照片数据库很大呢
but what if we had a very large database of photos, thousands
包含成千上万的照片信息
or tens of thousands of little pieces of information
这时我们就不能每次都从Flickr取回了
about photos, we couldn't be fetching that down every time
也不能存到NSUserDefault 我们需要一个数据库
and we couldn't store it in NS user default so we need a real database.
而且真正的数据库还让我们能够进行聪明的查询
Plus, a read database allows us to make really smart queries
关于现在我们的数据是什么
about what's, our data is right now.
如果只是显示在表格中 我们就很难查询了
We can't really query it at all, or almost not at all,
we're just kind of displaying it all in tables,
因此 下面我们需要让app的精密程度上升一个层次
so to take the next level of sophistication in our app, we need to do that.
Core Data是iOS7中一个非常强大的框架
So, core data is a very, very powerful framework in iOS7,
就它的作用而言 它绝对是最强大的之一
one of the most powerful in terms of what it can do.
一堂课多一点的时间 我只能讲到一些皮毛
I can only just barely scratch the surface in a lecture, in a little bit.
这周 我打算让你们理解基本知识
This week, I'm just going to try and get you the basics
你们之后需要…
and you're going to have to, you know,
如果未来你想做一个严谨的数据库app
if you want to do a serious database app in your future,
也许是期末项目或是以后的项目
maybe for your final project or beyond,
你需要额外去阅读相关内容
you'll need to do a little bit of extra reading up
因为Core Data内容太多了
because core data is massive.
就基础而言 它是一种创建对象的方式
But fundamentally, it's a base, it's a way of creating objects,
创建你要处理的Objective-C对象
objective C objects that you are going to deal with
并映射到 连接到SQL或XML数据库
that are mapped, or linked, to SQL, or XML, databases.
它是面向对象领域同数据库领域之间的桥梁
So, it's kind of a bridge between object-oriented land and database land,
数据库领域主要是SQL这些
and database land is dominated by things like sequel.
多少人知道SQL是什么
How many people here know what SQL is?
不是如何对其编程 知道它是什么就行了
Not know how to program SQL, but know what it is?
几乎所有人都知道
Yeah, so everyone, pretty much.
Core Data主要连接的就是SQL后台
So that's mostly what core data is hooked up is, is sequel backend.
Core Data是如何工作的呢
So how does core data work?
首先 你用Xcode中的工具创建一个可视映射
First, you create a visual map using a tool in Xcode.
拖放这类东西
So dragging and dropping and all that stuff,
在你的数据的面向对象的视图
so creating a mapping between an object-oriented view of your data
同SQL 或是数据的表格和行之间创建映射
and the sequel or tables and rows version of your data.
Core Data在创建这个映射之后
And core data allows really
能够很好进行无缝结合
that to be pretty seamless once you've created this mapping,
以后我会更进一步讲到这个
and we'll talk all about that and how it does that,
不过首先 我们来看看如何在Xcode中创建这个可视映射
but let's start by looking how we create this visual map in Xcode.
首先 创建映射我们需要选新文件
So, first, we create the map by doing new file,
往项目中加新东西
anytime we want to add something new to our project,
总需要点新文件 但在新文件中
we're going to do new file, but in new file, instead of doing
这里不再是Cocoa Touch或Objective-C类
like Cocoa Touch, objective C class, we're going to go down to
而是下面这里的Core Data
where it says core data, see that?
选择数据模型 不要错选映射模型
And pick data model, don't accidentally pick mapping model,
这里要的是数据模型 数据模型就是
its data model that you want here, okay, the data model is the mapping
面向对象的世界同数据库世界之间的映射
between the object-oriented world and the database world.
点这个
So you click that,
它会问你 叫什么名称 放到哪里
it's going to ask you what you want to call it and where you want to put it.
如果只有一个 有些人喜欢把模型文件叫Model
Some people like to call their model file, model, if they only have one.
有些人则喜欢用应用程序的名字
Some people like to name it the name of the application.
就像上周 如果我们要用Core Data
So like of last week, if we were doing core data we might have
我们可以叫它Shutterbug
called Shutterbug, the name.
有时 映射会有多个 这完全有可能
Sometimes you might have multiple mappings, and it is totally possible
在大程序中 很有可能存在多数据库 多映射
and in a big application you might well have multiple databases, multiple mappings,
你将有多个文件 因此 你取名称的时候
and so you would have multiple files, so you want to pick names
应该让映射对应于
for your mappings that kind of correspond
它们在程序中的用途
to what their purpose is inside your application,
这里我们使用默认值 也就是Model
so here we're going to take the default, which is just model,
可以看到这里 新文件得以创建
and you can see there, it creates this new file.
看导航器中 Model.xcdatamodeld
If you look over in the navigator over there, model dot xc data model d.
这是我们的映射 可视映射文件
And this is our mapping, our visual mapping file,
可以看到这里 它有一些组成部分
and you can see here that it has some components,
大多数我都会讲到
and we're going to talk about most of them.
分别是实体 属性 关系和取回属性
The components are entities, attributes, relationships, and fetch properties.
实体就像是对象 它们会映射到我们的对象
So entities are kind of like objects, they're going to map to our objects.
在数据库世界中 它们是表格
In the database world, they are tables.
属性就像是数据库中的列
Attributes are kind of like the columns in a table in database.
在面向对象的世界中 它们相当于对象的属性
In our object-oriented world, they're going to be properties on objects.
关系也是对象上的属性
Relationships are also properties on objects,
但它们是指针 指向数据库中的其它对象
but they are pointers to other objects in the database, okay,
或是指向一些别的对象
or pointers to a bunch of other objects, okay,
在数据库意义上 这就像是将不同表格连在一起
so this would be kind of like joins between tables in the database sense.
取回属性是一种
Fetch properties are kind of a
精密筹划的方式 得到一个指针指向其它属性
calculated way to have a pointer to some other properties.
这里出于时间考虑 我就不详细讲解取回属性了
I just have to cut something for time, so we're not going to talk about fetch properties,
理解了取回的工作方式后 它们就会很好理解
they're really not that complicated once you understand how fetching works,
这堂课比较靠后的时候我会讲到 到时候你们就懂了
much later in this lecture then you'll kind of get the idea.
你们会知道取回属性是怎么回事
Oh, I can see how maybe fetch properties would work
你们也可以去读说明文档
and then you can read the documentation and figure it out.
数据模型就包含这些 实体 属性 关系
So, that's what the data model consists of, entities, attributes, relationships.
这就是我们要讲的
That's what we're going to talk about.
就今天的例子而言
Let's, for our example today,
假设我们有一个类似于Shutterbug的程序
let's say we had a Shutterbug-like application
它有照片和拍照者
that had photos and photographers.
你们的作业是地点和照片
So your homework is going to be more places and photos.
而我周三的演示和这里的幻灯片
Our demo here, and the demo I do on Wednesday, and the slides,
则是照片和拍照者
are going to be photos and photographers.
这就是数据库中的两个东西
So those are the two things that are going to be in our database,
照片和拍照者
photos and photographers.
让我们为照片创建一个实体
So, let's create an entity for the photos.
点下面的添加实体 我们得到实体
So we click add entity down there at the bottom and we get this entity.
名称从Entity换成Photo
I'm going to change the name from entity to photo,
这将是数据库中我的照片对象
so this is going to be my photo object in the database.
然后我可以添加属性到照片对象
And then I can add attributes to my photo object by clicking
点击属性下方的+号就行了
on that little plus underneath where it says attributes there.
添加了一个 默认叫attribute
And when I add one, it adds one called attribute,
我要把这个名称改成title
I'm going to change the name of that to title,
照片都有标题 因此这里用title
so photos have a title, so I'm going to put a title in there.
注意到 这时右上方出现了红色的错误警告
And you notice as I do this, I get an error, a little red error warning up there.
为什么会这样
Why is that?
这是因为 title的类型没有定义
That's because the type of my title is undefined.
可以看到title旁边 它说类型未定义
You see where it says type, undefined next to title there?
这是不允许的
So that's not allowed.
你必须指定数据库中所有属性的类型
You have to specify the type of all the properties
你可以点击这个未定义
in your database, and so you just click on that undefined,
我选String 标题显然是字符串
I'm going to set this one to be a string, the title, obviously, is a string.
看看除了字符串还可以是什么
Now, what can some of these things be, besides strings?
还有数字 整数或是浮点数
Well they can be numbers, either integers or floating point numbers,
这些都将数据库表示为…
those are all representing the database as,
或者说在对象世界中 作为NSNumber
in your object world rather, as NS numbers.
实际上 数据库中的所有属性
All your properties, in fact, all the attributes in your objects in the database,
都是某种形式的对象
all their properties are going to be objects of some sort.
如果是字符串 那就是NSString对象
So NS string objects if their strings.
如果是整数 浮点数 双精度数字 布尔型数字
NS numbers if they're integers, floats, or double,
那就是NSNumber
or Booleans.
如果是日期 那就是NSDate
NS date if they're dates.
如果是二进制数据 那就是NSData
NS datas if they're binary data,
这是倒数第二个
that's the second to the bottom.
Transformable这个很有趣 这些是NSData对象
And then transformable is kind of an interesting one, those will be NS data objects,
它能提供一种可转换的对象
which will provide a little transformable object
能将其转化为别的类型
that will convert them to some other type,
甚至是struct这些
like even a struct, or something like that,
我们不打算深究Transformable
and we're not going to talk about transformables,
总之 可以在数据库中存储任何数据类型
but it is possible to store really any data type in the database
只要提供的是Transformable对象
as long as you provide a transformation object
它就能在NSData之间来回转换
that will convert them back and forth between NS data.
这里title很简单 它是一个字符串
So here, title is a simple one, it's a string,
这里我还要加其它一些属性
I'm going to add a whole bunch of other attributes here
可以看到 现在这里没报错了
that you kind of look, no more error there right now,
设成字符串后就没错误了
that I set it as string there's no more error.
我再加一些
If I add a whole bunch more,
我可以添加Flickr处获得的上传日期 这是日期
you can see I've added an upload date that I got from Flickr, so that's a date.
甚至缩略图数据
Even thumbnail data, so
假设我下载了缩略图数据
let's say I downloaded the thumbnail
这是Flickr照片的缩略图的图像数据
image data, the image data for a little thumbnail of my photo from Flickr,
我可以把这些数据存入数据库 作为NSData
I can actually put that data in the database as an NS data.
有些人问 这里能放多大的NSData
Some people ask, how big an NS data could I put in there?
我能放实际尺寸照片那么大的NSData吗
For example, could I put an NS data that is the real photo, the big, you know,
例如上MB大的照片
maybe a megabyte-size photo,
答案是 当然能
and the answer is absolutely, you can put them in here,
其实 有个开关你可以开启
in fact, there's a little switch that you can turn
明确你要存放大东西在这里 让其存到另一个文件
on that says I'm going to put something big here, store it in another file.
就算是存储在SQL文件中
But even if you store it in the sequel file,
通常也能处理 只是这不符合最佳实践 效率很低
it can usually manage it, it's probably not the best, most efficient way to do it,
不过没错 你确实可以将很大的数据存到Core Data中
but yes, you can store big data blobs in core data, as well.
这里是一些属性的例子
So, there's some example attributes.
我们换种方式来看这个
Let's look at this a different way.
看下面那里
If you see down at the bottom there
那里有编辑样式 我点这个
where it says editor style, right, I clicked on that
它展示的还是相同的东西 不过这次是以图像格式
and it switched over to showing the same thing, but in a graphical format.
看 这里是我的照片实体
So you see, here's my photo entity,
我可以看到属性 看到了吧 列在那里
I can see the attributes, see them there, listed there?
我还是可以在这个视图中创建一个实体
And I can still create an entity in this view, so I'm going
我来创建这个实体 也就是我的拍照者
to create another entity, which is my photographer.
创建这个实体 名称改成Photographer
I create that, entity, I'm going to change the name to photographer, it changes it.
我还可以在这个视图中添加属性
I can also add attributes in this view.
我往下到这个按钮 添加属性
So I just go down to this button here, add attribute,
这里添加属性 命名为name
I'm going to add an attribute here and I'm going to call it name,
这是拍照者的名字
so that's the name of the photographer.
你也可以编辑这些属性
You can also edit these attributes,
在这个视图中 通过点击它们
here in this view, by clicking on them.
点击名字
Alright, by clicking on the name,
然后到上面这里的属性检查器来
and then going up to this attributes inspector up here.
这就像是Xcode中另一个环境下的属性检查器
So this is kind of like the attributes inspector in other environments inside of Xcode,
点击这个
so if I click on that,
我就能够得到我的属性的一系列属性
you can see I get a bunch of attributes of my attributes.
这是name这个 它有名称
So here's the name one, and you can see there's the name of it
还有属性类型 这里是未定义
and there's the attribute type, which you can see is undefined,
这就是上面显示有错误的原因
that's why we have the error up there.
属性类型未定义
It's the attribute type undefined.
点这个 在下拉列表中将未定义改为字符串
So I'm going to click on that popup right there and change that undefined to be string.
拍照者的名字也是字符串
The photographers name is also a string.
我们于是有了这个
So we got that.
我还可以在这些对象之间创建关系
I can also create relationships between these objects,
照片和拍照者 很明显这两者具有关系
photos and photographers, clearly a photo and a photographer have a relationship.
拍照者拍出照片
A photographer takes photos.
照片是拍照者拍的
A photo is taken by a photographer.
要创建它们之间的关系 我可以control拖动
So I can create relationships between them by control, dragging,
我们很喜欢在Xcode中这样做 control拖动
that's how we like to do things in Xcode, we control, drag.
在照片和拍照者之间control拖动
So I'm going to control, drag between the photo and the photographer.
这就能够在它们之间创造新的关系
And it's going to create this new relationship between them.
这个关系将在两侧具有不同的名称
Now, the relationship will have a different name on each side.
在照片这一侧 我们称这个关系为
On the photo side, we're going to call this relationship
whoTook 意思是照片是谁拍的
who took, because this relationship is for the photo, who took it.
而拍照者一侧 我们则称之为photos
And on the photographer side, we're going to call it photos,
因为一个拍照者可能会拍多张照片 所以称之为photos
because a photographer can take multiple photos, so we'll call it photos.
这是相同的关系
So this is the same relationship,
不过它在这两个对象上各有一个属性
but it's going to have a property on each of these two objects,
在照片和拍照者两侧有所不同
photos and photographers, it's a little different.
注意 在拍照者这一侧看来
Now, notice that from a photographer's standpoint,
这个关系不是一一对应的
this relationship is not just a one-to-one,
因为拍照者可以照多张照片
because a photographer can take multiple photos,
在照片的检查器中可以看到 对于拍照者
and you can see them in the inspector for photos, on photographer,
这里有个类型说To One(对一)
there's a type that says to 1.
这意味着照片只有一个拍照者
That means it's a 1 to 1, relationship.
我可以把这改成To Many(对多) 这样做之后
I can actually change that to to many, and when I do that,
箭头的这一边变成了双箭头
you're going to see that I get a double arrow head, on that side of the pointer there,
这是说一个拍照者可以拍多张照片
that's saying a photographer can have multiple photos.
我们讲了 标题是字符串
Now, we talked about how title is a string
上传日期是日期 那whoTook和photos又是什么类型呢
and upload date is a date, what type is who took and photos?
是什么类型
What type are those?
它们也是这些对象的属性 但它们的类型是什么
Because they're just properties, as well, of these objects, but what's their type?
像photos这样对多的 实际上是NSSet
And it turns out that something like photos, which is a to many, is an NS set.
这就是它的类型
That's going to be its type.
就像title是NSString一样 photos是NSSet
Just like title is a NS string, photos is an NS set.
whoTook呢
What about who took?
whoTook实际上是NSManagedObject
Who took turns out to be a NS-managed object star,
它是指向NSManagedObject的指针
so it's a pointer to an NS-managed object.
NSManagedObject是数据库中所有对象的超类
NS-managed object is the super class for all objects in the database,
照片是NSManagedObject
okay, so photo is going to be an NS managed-object,
拍照者也是NSManagedObject
a photographer is going to be a NS-managed object.
在Objective-C代码中
In our objective C code, they're all going
它们都是NSManagedObject 显然whoTook指针
to be NS-managed objects, so, of course, the who took pointer,
作为指向拍照者的指针
which is a pointer to a photographer,
肯定会是NSManagedObject
is going to be an NS-managed object star,
我们会看到如何创建NSManagedObject的子类
and we're going to see how we can subclass NS-managed object
添加所有这些属性 等等
to add all these properties, and all this stuff,
那时它将是Photographer* 总之 whoTook就是这样
and then it would be a photographer star, but that's what who took is.
它不过就是一个指针而已
It's going to be exactly what you would expect, it's a pointer
指向另一个对象
to an object, which is that other object.
这里有个删除规则
This little delete rule right there, I'm not going
我不打算细讲
to go into detail about this,
删除规则明确了 删除拍照者后 whoTook会怎样
but the delete rule specifies what to do to who took, okay,
这是photos的删除规则
this is the delete rule for photos,
看到这里是photos 这个删除规则说
you see I'm inspecting photos there, this is the delete rule
如果我删除了一个拍照者 whoTook会怎样
that says if I delete a photographer, what happens to who took?
whoTook是一个指向拍照者的指针
Because who took was pointing to this photographer
如果我从数据库中删除了拍照者
and if I delete that photographer from the database,
这里的删除规则是nullify
and the answer here, this delete rule is nullify,
也就是whoTook会被设为nil
which means who took would be set to nil.
这里还有其它规则 例如cascade
But there are other rules, for example, cascade,
也就是说 删除拍照者时
which means delete, when you delete the photographer,
它指向的所有照片也都删除
delete every single photo that it points to.
cascade会把数据库中相关内容删干净
Cascade the delete throughout the database.
你需要知道这里是什么情况
So, you really want to know what you're doing here.
最安全的通常是nullify 将指针指向nil
The safest one is usually nullify, set things to nil,
如果指针指向nil时 你的数据库没有意义
but if your database doesn't make sense if a pointer points to nil,
这里你可能就需要更复杂的删除规则了
you might need more complicated delete rules there,
不过在作业中 你们不需要考虑更复杂的东西
but, in your homework, you won't need anything more complicated than that.
这就是在对象和数据库之间建立映射的方式
So that's basically how we build this map between objects and the database.
有了这个映射之后 你就能做很多事情
So, there's a lot of things that you can do once you have this map.
我们将聚焦于创建实体 属性
We're going to focus on the creating entities, attributes,
和关系 然后设定它们的属性
and relationships, and then setting their attributes
然后为它们进行查询 等等
and then querying for them and things like that.
总之 Core Data中 你能做的事很多
But there's a lot of other things you can do in core data,
我在最后会提到一些 如果有兴趣
I'll mention some of them at the end and you can go read up on it
你也可以去进一步了解
if you want to do more sophisticated database things.
创建了这个映射之后 如何访问代码中的这些东西呢
So, how do we access all of this stuff in our code, once we've created this map?
答案是 我们需要一个NSManagedObjectContext
And the answer is we need an NS-managed object context.
NSManagedObjectContext
An NS-managed object context.
这个context就是我们所需的衔接
This context is kind of the hook we need
无论是在数据库中创建对象 设置对象属性
to go create objects in the database, set attributes of objects in the database,
还是查询对象 都需要通过这个context
query for objects for the database, we all do these through this context.
如何获得一个context呢
So, how do we get a context?
做法有两种
Well, there's really two ways to do it.
一是使用UIManagedDocument这个类
One is you use this class UI managed object, which I'm, or managed document rather,
这个我会讲到
which I'm going to talk about.
另一种做法我不打算讲
And the second way, which I'm not going to talk about,
也就是alloc init一个NSManagedObjectContext
is that you can alloc init a NS-managed object context.
我不打算讲它的原因在于
The reason I'm not going to talk about it is,
你需要对context及其工作方式有一定了解
you got to know a little bit about context and how they work
知道它们如何保证线程安全这些
and how they do thread safety and things like that,
这些我不打算详细讲解
that I really don't want to get into the details of,
UIManagedDocument为我们处理好了所有这些
and that UI-managed document takes care of it all for us.
因此 我只打算讲解UIManagedDocument这种做法
So that's why I'm going to focus on the UI-managed document way.
如果你想了解如何
If you want to see how the way
alloc init一个NSManagedObjectContext…
of alloc initing an NS-managed object context,
要知道 这会变得非常复杂
because there's more then that you need to do, like you've got
你需要指定文件在哪 持久性存储在哪
to specify where the file is, the persistent store for it,
你需要把这个映射进来
you got to get this map into the picture.
不使用UIManagedDocument的话 这些都需要手动去做
All that stuff you'd have to do manually if you don't use UI-managed document.
如果你在创建一个新项目时
If you go when creating a new project
说master/detail 而不是单个视图控制器
and say master detail instead of single view controller,
会有一个按钮说 使用Core Data
it'll actually have a button that says use core data
创建这个新的之后 你就会看到很多
and when you create that new one, you'll see a whole bunch
Core Data代码 来处理所有这些工作
of core data code that does all this business in there.
不过 你没必要去看那个
But, there's no need for you to go look at that,
UIManagedDocument能更简洁地让你得到一个
UI-managed document is a much simpler, cleaner way to get yourself a UI,
NSManagedObjectContext 这正是我们想要的
or an NS-managed object context, which is what we're trying to do.
我们下面详细讲讲UIManagedDocument
So let's talk about UI-managed document and how that works.
它继承自一个叫作UIDocument的类
It inherits from a class called UI document.
UIDocument是一系列用于管理存储的机制
UI document is a whole bunch of mechanism for managing some storage.
UIManagedDocument
UI-managed document
将Core Data数据库放入某存储空间
puts a core data database in some storage.
因此 你是在管理Core Data数据库的存储
So you're managing the storage of your core data database,
你可以这样考虑UIManagedDocument
so you can think of UI-managed document as just like a thing
它为你容纳你的Core Data数据库
that contains your core data database for you.
你所做的只是打开或存储
And all you ever really do is open, or save,
或者说 打开或创建一个UIManagedDocument
or open or create, a UI-managed document
然后抓取它的ManagedObjectContext
and then grab its managed object context,
然后用它来做数据库
and then use it to do your database.
就是这样了
That's it.
这就是我们要讲的
So that's what we're going to talk about.
如何打开或创建一个UIManagedDocument
How to open, or create, a UI-managed document,
并获得它的ManagedObjectContext 然后再回头
and then get its managed object context and we'll dive back
考虑有了context 如何做Core Data
into now that we have a context, how do we do core data?
这就是创建UIManagedDocument的方式
So here's how you create a UI-managed document.
使用alloc init
You alloc init it.
它的指定初始化器是initWithFileURL
Its designated initializer is init with file URL,
你需要给它一个URL
you have to give it the URL
这是这个Core Data数据库存储的地方
where this core data database is going to be stored.
在黄色代码前面 我还写有四行白色代码
I've put these four lines of code that are in white, that are before the yellow here,
它们描述的是
they describe how
如何在用户文档目录中
you would create a document called My Document
创建一个叫作MyDocument的文档
in the users documents directory.
我们还没有谈到过存储文件 对吧
So when you're, we haven't really talked about storing files, right?
之前讲的内容都没有涉及到文件系统
We haven't accessed the file system at all, in anything we've ever done.
这需要通过这个类 NSFileManager(文件管理器)
We do this with this class NS file manager.
这一周我不打算讲这个
I'm not really going to cover that this week.
只需要知道 文件管理器能够
Suffice it to say the file manager can give you the URL
给你用户文件目录的URL
of the documents directory, for the user,
这就是第二行代码
that's what the second line of code there is,
然后你可以附加上你想要的文档名
and then you can just append whatever you want the name of your document to be,
例如 MyDocument 或是FlickrDatabase
like my document or Flickr database,
或是别的什么
or whatever you would want to call it.
这将是为你存储这一Core Data数据库的URL
This is going to be the URL where it's going to put that core data database for you.
有了URL以后
So now you have the URL,
你就可以用alloc init创建一个UIManagedDocument
you just say alloc init to create a UI-managed document.
不过UIManagedDocument
So, this UI-managed document though,
你只是alloc init了
you've only alloc init it,
你还没有把它创建到磁盘上
you haven't actually created it on disk.
它还不存在于磁盘上
It doesn't exist on disc yet.
我们需要做些工作 让它存在于磁盘上
So, we've got some work to do to make this thing exist on disc,
怎么做呢
and how do we do that?
如果它不存在 我们就需要创建它
Well, we have to create it if it doesn't exist,
如果它存在 我们就需要打开它
and we have to open it if it does exist.
换言之 我们之前用过它
In other words, we've used it before.
要弄清它是否存在于磁盘上
So to find out whether it exists on disc,
我们需要这个文件管理器的方法 fileExistsAtPath
we have to do this file manager thing, fileExistsAtPath.
我们有了URL 你说
So you have the URL to it, you say,
NSFileManager defaultManager
NS file manager default manager,
这就像是一个共享的文件管理器
that's like a shared file manager.
fileExistsAtPath
fileExistsAtPath,
它会返回一个布尔值 关于文件是否存在
it returns a Boolean whether the file already exists.
如果文件存在
If it does exist, in other words the file exists,
那么我们就会打开它
then we're going to open it, and the way we're going
这要使用UIManagedDocument方法
to open it is with the UI-managed document method
openWithCompletionHandler
open with completion handler.
如果不存在
If it doesn't exist,
那么我们将要创建文档到磁盘上 使用saveToURL
then we're going to create that document on disc with save to URL.
forSaveOperation
For save operation,
UIDocumentSaveForCreating是这里的参数
UI document save for creating is the argument we want there,
因为我们在创建这个文件 competionHandler
because we're creating this file, completion handler.
competionHandler是搞什么的
What's that completion handler business all about?
为什么这些打开和保存… 这里说是保存到URL
Okay, why do these open and save and create this, it says save
实际上则是在URL处创建
to URL, but really it's create at URL.
为什么有这个competionHandler
Why do they have this completion handler?
因为这些是异步的
Well, it's because these are asynchronous.
这两个方法 打开和创建
These two methods open and create, basically,
是异步的 并不立刻发生
are asynchronous, they don't happen immediately.
当你请UIManagedDocument为你打开或是创建什么时
When you ask the UI-managed document please open this or please create this for me,
它可能会需要一些时间
it might take it a little bit of time.
为什么要时间呢
Why might it take some time?
要时间的原因可能是
Well, it's possible it could take some time
文件系统需要一定时间 不过
because the file system takes a certain amount of time, but,
这里还涉及到其它我们不会讨论的东西
yeah, there's other things involved that we're not going to talk about,
例如iCloud 它可能需要
like iCloud, where maybe it needs
检查一些网络缓存或别的什么
to go check something with some network cache or something
因为这个文档将要到iCloud上 到其它设备上
like that, because this document is going to be on iCloud, okay, in other devices.
在Core Data数据库中使用UIManagedDocument
Now, one great thing about UI-managed document and using that
一大好处就在于 你处在通往iCloud的快通道上
to do your core data database, is you're on the fast-track to iCloud.
iCloud更容易 更直接
iCloud much easier, more straightforward
只要你使用UIManagedDocument
if you just start with UI-managed document.
不过你们只需要知道 这两个东西
But anyway, suffice it to say, these two things,
打开文档和创建文档 是异步的
opening a document and creating document, are asynchronous,
这意味着这个competionHandler 这一点小小的句法
which means that completion handler, that little syntax there,
这个competionHandler会被调用
but that completion handler gets called
回到你调用这些方法的线程上
back on the thread you called these methods on,
也就是主线程 因为这是UIManagedDocument
which has got to be the main thread because this is UI-managed document,
这是一个UIKit对象 这些方法的调用
this is a UI kit object, you have to call these methods
需要在主线程 主队列上
on the main thread, the main queue.
这个competionHandler
So that completion handler
在完成时被调用回主队列上
will get called back on the main queue when it's done.
无论多久 它会被调用
No matter how long it takes, it'll get called later
这是完成时 然后在这个代码块
when it's done, and then in that block,
你可以做你想做的事
you just start doing what you want to do.
我来讲讲
Alright? So let's talk about what you might,
这是怎么样的
how this might look to
看文件是否存在
see if the file exists
如果存在就打开 如果不存在就创建
and if it does open it and if it doesn't, create it,
它是这样的
it looks something like this.
在competionHandler中
And inside that completion handler,
如果成功打开或成功创建了的话
if you successfully opened or successfully created it,
你会调用一些你的方法
you're going to call some method of yours,
我将它称作documentIsReady
I've called it document is ready, you can call
你也可以起别的名称
that method anything you want, that says okay,
文档已就绪 你现在可以用它了
the documents ready to go, now you can go use it.
两种情况下我都做了相同的事情
Alright? And I'm doing the same thing in either case.
苹果在这里没给打开或创建这样的方法 显得有些懒
It's a little bit of a bummer that there's no method like open or create,
苹果只给出了这些东西
and it just does it all in once, that you have
只有fileExists这些 不过你也没办法
to do this file exist business, but you do, so you're going
这段代码几乎会出现在任何
to have this little sequence of code
使用UIManagedDocument的app中
in almost any app that uses a UI-managed document.
这有些愚蠢 因为都是很简单很类似的东西
It's kind of silly, because it's all very, very simple, similar,
不过它就是这样的
if then there, but that's what it looks like.
documentIsReady方法又是怎样的呢
So now, what does that document is ready method look like?
大致是这样的
It looks something like this.
在documentIsReady方法最开始
One thing I might do at the beginning
我可以检查文档的状态
of my document is ready is check the state of the document
看它是否处于正常状态
to see if it's in the normal state,
正常状态是说 它准备好了
normal state means this guys is ready to go.
它可以有哪些状态呢
What other states could it be in?
状态还可以是关闭
Well it could be in the state closed,
关闭是说 还没有打开
closed means you haven't opened it yet
或者还没有创建
or you haven't created it yet.
这两种都是关闭状态
Either case it's going to be closed.
关闭状态的文档不能使用
You cannot use a document once in the closed state.
还有一些状态 例如保存错误
Some of these other states, like there was a saving error
或是编辑暂时禁用
or editing is temporarily disabled
因为iCloud中有其他人正在编辑这个文档
because someone else is editing this document in iCloud
例如它在更新
and its updating, for example.
这门课中你不会碰到这些
You're not going to run into those in this class,
但你应该知道有这些东西
but you should know that they are there.
在最开始检查这个
So, checking that, at the beginning to, you know,
这是一个位掩码 因此我使用了那个&符号
it's a bit mask there, that's why I'm using that ampersand,
我只是检查那个位 看我的文档是否在正常状态
right, I'm just checking that bit, do my documents stay normal?
看文档是否准备就绪
Just to see if the document is ready to go.
这是第一件事 检查其状态
So that might be the first thing I do is check its state
确保它就绪了 如果没就绪 例如是关闭的
to make sure it's ready to go, if it's not, like if it was closed,
那我就需要回头尝试打开或创建它
then I might go back and try to open it, or create it again.
如果有错误 我可能会等一下 再试一下 等等
If it's got an error, I might wait awhile and try this again, or something like that.
无论如何 假设我的文档处在正常状态 再怎么做呢
So anyway, let's say I have this document in a normal state, now what am I going to do?
我要抓取那个NSManagedObjectContext
Now I'm going to grab that NS-managed object context
开始做一些Core Data方面的事
and go start doing some core data stuff.
就是这样
And that's it.
我们就是这样开始
So this is how we get started.
在具体考虑如何处理NSManagedObjectContext前
Now, before we dive into what we're going to do with that NS-managed object context,
我还要再讲几点UIManagedDocument的内容
a couple more things about UI-managed document,
一是 它是自动保存的
one is that it is auto saved.
你不需要手动保存
You do not have to save it.
你可以用这里的方法来保存它
And you can save it using this method you see here,
但一般我们不这样做 我们会让它自动保存
but generally we don't, we let it auto save.
存储方式还是原来那个方法
The way we save it is with the same method
我们说UIDocumentSaveForOverwriting
that we used before, but we say UI document save for overwriting,
不过我们一般不会调用这个方法
but generally, we don't call this method.
我们让它自动保存
We let it auto save.
理解这个非常重要
So that's an important thing to understand.
第二点 关闭文档
Second thing, closing the document.
实际上 它也能自动关闭
Well, it kind of auto closes, as well.
什么时候关闭呢
When does it close?
当没有任何强指针指向它时
When there are no more strong pointers to it.
换言之 当没有任何强指针指向它时
In other words, when there are no more strong pointers to it,
当它要离开堆时 它就会自动关闭
when it's going to leave the heap, it gets closed automatically.
因此 你一般也不用调用关闭 虽然你可以这么做
So you generally don't call a close either, but you can do that as well.
关闭和保存一样 也是异步的
And close, just like saving, are asynchronous,
你需要实现completionHander 来做你想做的事
and you got to implement these completion handlers to do whatever you want
当它们完成关闭或是完成保存时
when they're done closing or done saving.
有问题
Question?
对
Correct. Yes.
问题是 关闭之前它是否会自动保存
So the question, does it auto save before closing?
当然会
Absolutely.
你要它关闭 或是不再有强指针指向它时
If you say close, or if you stop having a strong pointer to it,
它就会保存然后关闭
it will save and then close.
关于保存和自动保存我还想说一点
One thing I will say about saving, the auto saving,
在调试时
when you're in debugging, you know,
你处在开发模式 你在调试
when you're in development mode and you're debugging,
有时学生会有些困扰
sometimes students will get a little confused,
因为他们会做点什么
because they'll go and they'll do something,
更新数据库 然后停在调试器中
update their database, and then they'll stop in the debugger,
改一下代码 再次运行 结果数据不见了
made a code change and run again, and the data won't be there.
因为它没有自动保存的机会
Well, because it didn't have a chance to auto save.
在开发模式中 你需要明确放一些保存进来
So when you're in development mode, you might want to throw in some explicit saves
如果你总要在调试器中点停止的话
if you're going to be hitting stop in the debugger all the time.
好 我们再来讨论相同文档上
Alright, so let's talk about multiple instances
UIManagedDocument的多实例
of UI-managed document on the same document.
能不能 我对文件URL进行alloc init
Am I allowed to alloc init file URL
来创建一个UIManagedDocument
to create a UI-managed document, and then somewhere else
然后其他人对相同文件URL进行alloc init
in my code, alloc init file URL, the same URL, and have two
让两者着眼于相同文档 你可能会认为这行不通
of them looking at the same document, you might think, oh that can't work,
但实际上 这完全可以
but actually it does, it works perfectly fine.
完全没问题
It works absolutely no problem,
两者有自身的ManagedObjectContext
the two have their own managed object context
这是不同的 不过context都着眼于
that are different, but they're both, contexts are looking
相同的数据库 它们都发生变化时 会发生保存
at the same database and when they both make changes, it's going to save.
这也有可能出现问题
There is the possible problem though
一个UIManagedDocument实例试图进行一种操作
that one set of changes in this instance of the UI-managed document,
另一个却有冲突
and this one might conflict.
一个可能想删除对象
They might be trying to, one's trying to delete an object,
但同时 另一个可能想设置属性
but another one is trying to set an attribute of it at the same time.
如果确实是多实例 冲突是很有可能出现的
So, if you do have this, it is possible to get conflicts,
不过通常 多实例
but usually if we have multiple instances,
只有一个能写 其它那些只能读
it's because we have one writer and many readers.
两个控制器或什么 每个都能作出修改
It's pretty rare to have two separate controllers or something, each having a document
这是很罕见的情况
and their both making changes, that's pretty rare.
同时作出修改就更不用说了
Especially both making changes at the same time,
屏幕上只有这么些空间可供修改决策的作出
there's only so much screen for changes to be being made on.
这里有一点需要小心
One thing to be careful of here is
如果一个文档修改了数据库
that if one document changes the database,
另一个并不能自动看到相应变化
the other one doesn't automatically see those changes.
你可能会说
It's not like
哦 我加了一个对象到一个ManagedDocument
oh I added an object in one managed document,
哦 我在另一个中看不到
oh, I don't see it in the other one.
为什么看不到呢
Why don't you see it?
看不到是因为context不同
Well you don't see it because they have different context,
不同的NSManagedObjectContext
different NS-managed object contexts,
不过你仍然是在修改相同的数据库
but you're still modifying the same database.
那如何知道另一个文档是否进行了修改呢
So how could you find out, if you wanted to find out if another document is doing,
答案是 广播站
and the answer is, the radio station.
我们可以使用NSNotification
We could use NS notification.
这是一个例子 有一个控制器
And so, here's an example of having a controller,
到屏幕上时 开始监听
when it comes on screen, start listening at,
不同文档的ManagedObjectContext
to the managed object context, there, of a different document.
不是它打开的文档 而是别的
Not the document it has open, but some other,
UIManagedDocument的其它实例
some other instance of a UI-managed document,
而且它在找广播站
and it's looking for the radio station,
NSManagedObjectContextDidSaveNotification
NS-managed object context did save notification.
另一个文档自动保存时 它就会
So whenever that other document auto saves, then it's going
获得NSNotification说 哦 它变了
to get a NS notification saying oh, it changed.
我把这个方法叫contextChanged 或是别的什么
Alright? And I'm going to call this method context changed or whatever.
这个发生时我要做什么呢
And what would I do when that happens?
两点 一是我可以重新取回我的所有对象
Well, two things, one, I could just refetch all my objects.
我知道数据库发生了变化
Okay, I know the database is changed,
我重新取回它们 我还没讲取回
I'll just refetch them all, we haven't talked about fetching,
不过 我可以重新取回 更新所有东西
but I could refetch and get a fresh set of everything.
但实际上 这个ContextDidSaveNotification
But, actually this context change did save notification,
会给你一个数组
gives you an array,
在它用户信息中的是一个字典
inside of its user info is a dictionary,
有三个数组 这是所有变化了的对象的列表
with three arrays that are a list of all the objects that changed.
你可以把这些变化合并到你的context中
And you can merge those changes
使用这个NSManagedObjectContext方法
into your context using this NS-managed object context
mergeChangesFromContextDidSaveNotification
method, merge changes from context did save notification,
你把notification给它
you just give it the notification,
它会自动将所有变化合并到你的context中
and it'll automatically merge all those changes into your context,
非常酷
which is pretty cool.
这是一个很酷的方法
This is a very cool method.
这个方法的酷经常会被人们低估
Very underappreciated coolness of this method.
你在监视其它context
So you're watching some other context that's
同你的具有相同数据库 但context不同
on the same database as yours, but it's a different context,
你获得一个notification 将变化合并到你的里面
you get a notification, you can merge those changes into yours,
就好像这些变化是你做出的一样
as if you had made those changes.
两个文档同时存储时也没问题
And it's all going to be fine when both documents save
因为你合并了相同的变化
because you're merging in the same changes
Core Data会自动处理
and this is, core data automatically deals
当相同变化由两个不同context同时完成
with when the same change is being made by two different contexts,
只有冲突的才会让你产生问题
only when conflicting ones happen is it a problem for you.
这些都能奇妙地良好运作
So this all kind of just magically works.
这是监视另一个context
So that's watching another context.
作业中可能不需要这些
Probably not going to be necessary in homework,
你们或许会采取一种不同策略
because you're probably going to take a different strategy,
也就是只有一个UIManagedDocument
which is have one managed document, UI-managed document,
然后将它的context用到app的所有地方
and you use its context everywhere in your app.
这样做显然更简单
That's kind of a simpler way to do it,
作业中 我建议你们这样做
and that's what I recommend for your homework.
我们会在演示中看到 演示中我会展示这个
And we'll see in the demo, I'm going to do that in the demo.
好 现在我们有了NSManagedObjectContext
Alright. So now we have an NS-managed object context
来自于我们的文档 我们能用它做什么
that we got from our document, what can we do with it?
我们可以插入和删除对象
Well, we can insert and delete objects,
我们可以修改属性 我们还可以查询对象
we can change attributes, and we can query for objects.
我们来谈谈这些
So let's talk about doing all those things.
首先是插入
Let's start with inserting.
假设我要添加一张新照片 或是一个新的拍照人
So let's say I want to put a new photo, or put a new photographer
到数据库中 我可以用这个方法
into the database, I do that with this method right here,
这是一个NSEntityDescription上的类方法
it's a class method on NS entity description
叫insertNewObjectForEntityForName
called insert new object for entity for name
inManagedObjectContext
in managed object context.
可以看到 没有context 我是无法插入对象的
So you can see, I can't insert an object without having a context.
必须context牵线搭桥 才能插入对象到数据库中
The context is the hook that lets you insert things
或是查询 或是做别的任何事情 context是必须的
in the database or query or anything, so you have to have a context.
第一个参数@"Photo" 这是实体的名称
And, that first argument, at sign photo, that is the name of the entity.
记得在映射中我创建了一个Photo实体吗
So remember in the mapping thing when I made a photo entity
我还创建了一个Photographer实体 这就是实体名
and I made a photographer entity, this is a string which is the name.
这里创建一张照片
So here I am making a photo.
它返回什么呢
And what does it return?
它会返回NSManagedObject *photo
It returns NS-managed object star photo,
我讲过 数据库中的所有对象
and I told you that all of the objects in the database
都是NSManagedObject或其子类
are NS-managed objects or subclasses thereof.
这就是实际情况
And, in fact, that's exactly what happened.
这里就会创建一个 并返回出来
So this is just going to make one for you and return it.
它会是空的
It's going to be blank, or empty.
这可能意味着 所有属性都是nil
Now, that could mean that all of its attributes are nil,
但我们在Xcode中没看到这个
but we didn't see this in Xcode,
在Xcode中检查属性时
but it, when you inspect a property in Xcode,
你可以指定一个默认值
you can actually specify a default value,
它会用那个值
and it'll have that value.
或许 你希望它让上传日期
So maybe you want it to have the upload date
默认为对象创建的日期或是别的什么
by default be the date the object was created or something,
你可以创建某个固定日期
you can go in and create some fixed date
或者 你希望标题总是至少为空字符串
or you want the title to always be at least the empty string
诸如此类 你可以设置默认
or something like that, you can set defaults,
在Xcode中 这些需要是常数
they have to be constants basically, in Xcode,
在这些字段处 NSObject会带着这些默认设置回来
to do that and NS object will come back with those defaults set in those fields,
否则就是nil
and otherwise nil.
如果不想设置这些默认值
But if you don't do any of that default setting,
这个照片中的一切属性都将是nil
all the properties in this photo will be nil.
标题是nil 副标题是nil
So the title will be nil, subtitle will be nil,
whoTook是nil 都是nil
the who took will be nil, it'll all be nil.
很好 现在我有了对象 那如何设定属性呢
So, great, now I have an object, how do I set those attributes?
我要设定标题
I want to set the title.
我要设定副标题 我还要设定whoTook
I want to set the subtitle, I even want to set who took?
怎么做呢
How do I do that?
这要用到KeyValueCoding协议
You do that using the key value coding protocol.
你们其实已经用过这个协议了
And you've already used this protocol actually.
它是valueForKey
It is value for key,
setValue forKey
set value for key,
valueForKeyPath
value for key path,
和setValue forKeyPath
and set value for key path.
这个协议 由NSDictionary实现
So this protocol, which is implemented by NS dictionary,
例如 这就是我们使用valueForKeyPath的方式
for example, that's how we used value for key path
在NSDictionary中
in those NS dictionaries, to do the things like
做description._content这样的事 记得吗
description dot under bar contents, remember that,
来自Flickr
from Flickr?
这就是NSManagedObject的工作方式
This is how NS-managed object works.
它实现了所有这些 而且你可以说valueForKey
It implements all these and you can say value for key,
@号 引号 标题 这就能得到照片的标题
at sign quote title, and you can get the title of a photo.
你也可以说setValue 然后是你想设的
Or you can say set value, whatever you want,
forKey @号 引号 标题
for key at sign quote title,
这就为标题设了值 很简单
and set the value of a title, simple as that.
valueForKey setValue forKey
Value for key, set value for key.
这方面有问题吗
Any questions about that?
好 显然 键只是一个字符串
Okay. So, the, the key is obviously just a string,
早些时候我们创建的可视映射中的属性名
the name of the property in your visual map that we built earlier.
值只是一个对象 例如如果是标题 那就是NSString
The value would be just an object, like an NS string, if it was a title,
如果上传日期 那就是NSDate
and NS date if it was the upload date
如果是缩略图数据什么的 那就是NSData
and NS data if it was the thumbnail UR, thumbnail data or whatever.
你还可以用setValue forKey来设定关系
You can also set, using set value for key, the relationships.
如果你有一个拍照者
So if you had a photographer,
或许你也插入了实体描述这些
which maybe you inserted with that entity description thing,
有了拍照者 你可以说
so now you have photographer, as well, you can just say the,
照片 setValue 引号 whoTook
the photo set value, quote who took,
设置值
set the value,
拍照者
the photographer,
forKey 引号 whoTook
for the key quote who took.
有趣的是 如果你设置whoTook的值
Now, what' really interesting is that if you set that value who took,
拍照者中的照片集合将会自动更新
the photo set, in the photographer, will automatically be updated.
你不需要同时设置关系的两侧
You do not have to set both sides of the relationship.
反之亦然
And vice versa.
如果我有一个拍照者 我在其照片集中添加一张照片
If I have a photographer and I add a photo to its photos set,
whoTook也会自动设置
it'll automatically set who took.
这是因为这个数据库 需要维持自身的内部一致性
And that's because this database has to maintain self internal consistency
Core Data会为你做所有这些 这非常酷
and so core data does that all for you, which is really cool?
你可以设置任何一侧
So you can set either side
另一侧都会自动设置
and it'll automatically set the other side.
之前我说过 很多的是NSSet
As I said before, the too many ones are NS sets,
不那么多的是NSManagedObject
and the non-too many ones are just NS-managed object stars.
你进行的所有这些修改
Now, all these changes that you're making,
插入对象 设置各种属性 这些都只发生在内存中
inserting objects, setting all those properties, those only happen in memory.
不发生在磁盘上 直到context得到保存
They're not happening on disc, until the context is saved.
context有一个保存方法
Now the context has a save method.
你可以去看NSManagedObjectContext
If you go look in NS-managed object context,
它有一个保存方法 但你不会调用它
it has a save method, but you're not going to call that, because you're going
因为你会让UIManagedDocument自动保存context
to let UI-managed documents auto save, save the context.
如果你保存文档 或者 你也可以发送信息给context
Alright? So if you save the document or you can actually send a message
来保存它自身
to the context to save itself.
无论哪种方式 它都会存到磁盘上 但这之前
Either way, it will save out to disc, but until then,
所有修改都只存在于内存中
all the changes you're making are just in memory.
Core Data内建有很让人难以置信的撤销与重做
Now, core data has an incredible undo and redo built into it.
进行一些修改 然后说undo 修改就会撤销
To, you make some changes, you say undo, it undoes them.
你还可以批处理 你可以撤销一组操作
And you can batch them up and you can undo things as a group
你可以撤销最近一连串操作
and can undo just the last chain, I can't,
我没时间讲所有这些 不过这非常酷
I don't have time to talk about any of that, but it's really, really cool.
任何修改数据库数据的时候
So anytime you have a situation where you're changing database
用户或许会要撤销 Core Data在这方面很棒
and the user wants to be able to maybe undo, core data's awesome for that.
就像NSManagedObjectContextDidSaveNotification一样
Just like you get UI, or NS-managed object did save notifications,
你还可以有UIManagedDocumentDidSaveNotification
you can also get UI-managed document did save notification.
你可以使用这个广播站
So you can sign up for that radio broadcast
弄清什么时候整个文档得到了保存
and find out when the whole document did save.
这两种其实是半斤八两
Kind of six, one-half dozen in the other in this case,
因为如果文档保存了
because if the documents get saved,
那context显然也保存了
then definitely the context is going to be saved, as well.
像这样调用valueForKey和setValue forKey
Calling value for key and set value for a key like this though,
会导致一些很丑陋的代码
it kind of results in some ugly code.
因为它没有类型检查 valueForKey
Because it's not type checked, right, value for key
和setValue forKey
and set value for key,
或许我该说setValue:forKey:
that should be set value colon for key colon,
它只取id
that just takes ID.
返回id 所以说 这里没有任何类型检查
Right? Returns ID, so it's really not type checking any of that stuff,
而且 最终会有很多字符串字面量
and also, you end up with a lot of literal strings,
例如@"thumbnailURL"
like at sign quote thumbnail URL
如果你在可视映射中修改了这个的名称
and if you ever changed the name of that in your visual map,
所有代码都将静静地停止工作 你甚至知都不知道
all your code would just stop working silently and you wouldn't know, so,
我们这里实际想要的是属性
really what we want here is properties.
我们希望能够设置标题 副标题和缩略图URL
We want to be to set the title and subtitle and thumbnail URL
所有这些在我的照片中使用属性和点符号
and all that stuff in my photo using properties and dot notation.
要做这些 我们需要为Photo创建一个子类
So, all we need to do to do that is create subclasses for photo,
同时为Photographer创建一个子类
and a subclass for photographer.
NSManagedObject的子类 对吧
Subclasses of NS-managed object, right?
子类会实现所有这些属性
And the subclasses will implement all these properties,
而且Xcode非常棒 它会帮你打理好这些
and, of course, because Xcode is so nice, it's going to do that for you,
下面讨论一下如何
so let's talk about now how
在Xcode中 为Photo和Photographer创建子类
in Xcode we can make it generate subclasses for photo and photographer.
回到我的可视映射 点选Photo和Photographer
So I'm going back to my visual map, I'm going to select photo and photographer,
然后从编辑器菜单
and then I'm going to, from the editor menu,
选重要的菜单项 叫
I'm going to pick this all important menu item called
创建NSManagedObject子类
create NS-managed object subclass.
这正是我们要做的
Because that's exactly what's it going to do.
这样做之后 它会问
And when I do that, it's going to say okay,
哪个模型 这里我们只有一个
which of your models, okay, we only have one,
Model.xcdatamodeld 不过 这里也可以有多个
model dot xc data model d, but you could have multiple,
你希望为哪个模型生成NSManagedObject的子类
which of your models do you want to generate managed object subclasses for?
我们选择这个模型 它会问
So we'll just pick model, and then, it says okay, well,
你想为哪些类 哪些实体创建子类
which of the classes, which of the entities you want to create a subclass for?
两个我都选上 Photo和Photographer
We'll pick them both, both photo and photographer here, and,
它又问 存在哪呢
it's going to say where do you want to store them,
存在存其它东西的地方
we'll store then where we store everything else, and then,
有了 Photo.m和.h 以及Photographer.m和.h
bingo, photo dot m and h, and photographer dot m and h,
看到了吗 这些得以创建
you see those there, that got created for us?
这些是NSManagedObject的子类
So, those are subclasses of NS-managed object,
将一个对象插入数据库时
and when you insert an object in the database,
或是取回对象 这个我们还没讲到
or get one back on a fetch, which we haven't talked about,
如果你将一个对象插入数据库 当它返回时
if you insert an object in the database, when it comes back,
它将不再是NSManagedObject
instead of being an NS-managed object star,
而是Photo *或Photographer
it's going to be a photo star, or a photographer star.
这会自动生效
It's just going to automatically work, that
这个insertNewObjectForEntityForName方法
insert entity for, for entity for name method,
我总是记不清楚这个名字
which I can never remember the name of,
如果有子类的话 返回的将是子类
that will return, if there's a subclass to be had, the subclass.
我们来看看这个的代码
Alright, so let's look at the code of this,
例如我们看看Photo.h 可以看到
let's look at photo dot h, for example, so you can see,
Photo.h中有很多@property
that photo dot h has made an at sign property for all
对应于照片的数据库属性
of my database properties for photos,
有标题 照片URL
see title, photo URL,
它们是正确的类型 NSDate NSData
they're the right type, NS date, NS data,
甚至whoTook的类都正确
even who took is the right class.
whoTook是一个Photographer
You see who took is a photographer star.
有时 做这个时
Now, sometimes you'll just, do this
whoTook将仍然是NSManagedObject
and who took will still be an NS-managed object star.
为什么呢
Why does that happen?
这是因为这是一次生成
That's because this is a one-pass generation,
如果照片是在拍照者之前生成
and if it happens to generate photo before it generated photographer,
它就不知道拍照者 这个就做不了
it won't know about photographer and it won't be able to do this.
如果是这样 回到你的映射
If that happens, just go back to your map
重新生成 这时它们就都存在了
and generate them again, and this time they'll both exist,
这就能够得到正确的东西了
beforehand, and so it'll, it'll make the right thing.
你想重新生成多少次都行
So you can regenerate as many times as you want, and, in fact,
实际上 我们在变更方案
we're going to be regenerating as we change scheme,
添加实体 添加属性时
add more entities, add more properties,
也会不断进行重新生成
we're going to be redoing that regenerate all the time.
有问题
Question?
是 问题是
Yes. So, let's, the question is
讲讲为什么那上面用@class Photographer
tell me about that at sign class photographer towards the top there.
为什么不是#import Photographer.h
Why is that not pound sign import photographer dot h,
在Objective-C中
well, in objective c,
如果你只是想声明某个东西是某个特定类型
if all you want to be able to do is declare that something is of a certain type,
你不需要所有方法
and you don't need all the methods,
你也不打算调用任何方法
you're not going to call any of the methods or anything like that,
这时就可以用@class指令
then you can just do this at sign class directive,
你也可以对协议这样做 你可以说@protocol
you can do the same thing for protocols, you can say at sign protocol, whatever,
声明这个协议存在
and just declare that protocol exists, so I don't,
我不打算调用或是实现任何方法
I'm not going to call any of the methods in it or implement any of the methods.
这是一种前向声明
So it's kind of a forward declaration
因为最终 会用到这个的任何人
because eventually anyone who's going to use this is going to
都会开始调用Photographer方法 会导入它
start calling photographer methods and they're going to import it,
不过 这是一种避免编译器警告的方式
but this is just a way to suppress that compiler warning,
它没有说未知类Photographer
so it doesn't say unknown class photographer,
同时又不用导入Photographer.h
without having to import photographer dot h.
这让它们保持独立
That kind of keeps them independent,
这样你就不需要在不想的时候生成Photographer.h
that way you wouldn't have to generate photographer dot h if you didn't want to,
你只想要Photo 这是可以的
you just wanted photo and then that could be,
其实并不是这样
although, that wouldn't be true
因为这时它就是NSManagedObject 无论如何
because then it would be NS-managed project, but anyway,
如果你在这里有NSManagedObject
if you have NS-managed object, there,
你只需重新生成它们
then just generate them again.
我们再来看Photographer.h
Alright, so let's look at photographer dot h,
可以看到 它有name和photos两个属性
you can see it has name and photos, right, as promised.
photos是一个NSSet 看到了吗
Photos is an NS set, you see that?
这里它还给了我好多方法
It also gave me a whole bunch of methods here
用于将照片加入到照片集中
for adding photos to the photo set,
这个NSSet是一个NS不可变集合
because that NS set, that's an NS immutable set,
如果我想设置一个照片列表
so if I wanted to set the list of photos,
我需要创建一个可变集合
I'd have to create a mutable set,
将我要的所有照片对象放到里面
put all the photo objects that I wanted in there,
然后设置整个东西
and then set the whole thing.
你知道的 我的拍照者点photos等于整个集合
You know, say, you know, my photographer dot photos equals a whole set.
通过addPhotosObject或removePhotosObject
With add photos object, or remove photos object,
我可以一次加一张照片
I can just add one photo at a time.
这些都是很便利的方法
So it's just kind of, those are convenience methods
用于将照片加到照片集
for adding photos to that photoset.
再来看看这些.m文件
So let's look at the dot m's of these though.
这些.m你们觉得会是怎样的呢
And what do you imagine these dot m's look like?
像集合setter和getter
Like set setters and getters?
或是@synthesize 诸如此类
Or, at sign synthesizes or something like that?
答案是 这些都没有
And the answer is none of that.
这些的实现只是@dynamic 用于所有这些属性
The implementations of these just say at sign dynamic for all of the properties.
@dynamic是什么玩意 我们从没见过这个
Now, what the heck is at sign dynamic, we never seen that before?
@dynamic其实也就是说
At sign dynamic basically means
我知道我在做什么 不要为此发出警告
hey I know what I'm doing, don't generate a warning for this.
NSManagedObject在这里是做什么的呢
And what does NS-managed object do, in this case,
这里既没有@synthesize
since there's no at sign synthesize,
也没有setter和getter
there's no setters and getters here,
实现只是避免发出警告而已
the implementation just suppresses the warning, basically,
答案是 Objective-C 运行时
and the answer is objective C, the run time,
有一个避陷机制
has a trapping mechanism where
如果发送信息给一个对象
if you send a message to an object,
对象不懂这个方法
and it doesn't understand that method, right,
无法实现 这就陷住了
it doesn't implement that, it can trap.
它会尝试别的办法
And go try to figure out something else to do.
以免崩溃 或是说无法响应选择器
Without crashing or saying does not respond to selector.
而NSManagedObject 当它获得了不理解的信息时
And, NS-managed object, when it gets sent a message it doesn't understand,
它会尝试valueForKey
it tries to do value for key,
或是setValue forKey
or set value for key on it.
如果这个行不通
Alright? And if that doesn't work,
这时它就会说 无法识别选择器
then it says does not recognize selector,
如果行得通 那就成了
but if it does work, then it just works.
这就是这里的情况
So that's what's going on here,
对于NSManagedObject
NS-managed object
setter getter或其它方法发送给它时 它会陷住
traps when setters and getters or any method is sent to it
它会尝试valueForKey和setValue forKey
and it tries to do value for key and set value for key,
如果行得通 那就行了 如果行不通 它就会说
and if it can, all is good, and if it can't, then it says,
无法理解选择器
does not understand selector.
都理解了吗
Everyone understand that?
这个@dynamic只是说 别发出警告
So this at sign dynamic just says don't generate a warning
我没实现setter和getter 但我知道我在做什么
that I don't implement the setter and getter, because I know what I'm doing.
好
Alright.
有了这些子类 如何使用它们
So, so now that I have these subclasses, how do I use them
来使用点符号访问我的属性呢
to access my attributes using dot notation,
现在我说 NSEntityDescription
and so now when I say NS entity description,
insertNewObjectForEntityForName
insert new object for entity for name,
inManagedObjectContext
in managed object context,
我没说 NSManagedObject *photo等于那个
instead of saying NS-managed object star photo equals that,
而是说 Photo *photo等于那个
I say photo star photo equals that,
insertNewObjectForEntityForName
insert a new object for entity for name,
返回的是id类型
by the way, returns an ID,
两种情况下 编译器都不会警告你或是报错
so the compiler is not going to warn you or give an error in either case.
不过如果你说Photo *photo=那个
But if you say photo star photo equals that,
那么你就可以说 photo.title =
then you can just say photo dot title equals,
你想要的标题
whatever you want the title to be,
例如像我这样是从Flickr下载的 我可能会说
like if I'm downloading this Flickr, I might say
flickrData objectForKey:FLICKR_PHOTO_TITLE
Flickr data object for key Flickr photo title,
从来自Flickr的字典中将其取出
get it out of that dictionary that came from Flickr
我刚在数据库中设置了那个标题
and I'm just setting that title in my database.
100%完全符合大家的预期
Exactly 100 percent what you would think it would be.
你还可以做如下这些事情
Here's a whole bunch of other examples of what you would do,
你显然可以调用getter
you can also obviously call the getter,
我可以说 NSString *myThumbnail
so I could NS string star my thumbnail
= photo.thumbnailURL
equals photo dot thumbnail URL.
获得那个缩略图URL
Get that thumbnail URL out of there, that,
注意 数据库中不能直接放URL
notice that you can't put URL's in the database,
你需要用字符串 然后把它们转换成URL
you have to put strings and convert them to URL's.
我可以说 photo.lastViewedDate = [NSDate date]
I could say photo dot last view date equals NS date date, okay,
NSDate中的date方法能给出当前日期和时间
the date method in NS date gives the current date and time,
我可以把这设为照片最近浏览的日期
I could set that as the photo's last viewed date.
我显然还可以说
I can even, I can obviously do
photo.whoTook = 某个拍照者对象
photo dot who took equals some photographer object,
我甚至还可以说 photo.whoTook.name =
but I can even say photo dot who took dot name equals
拍照者的名字
the name of the photographer.
如果我有一张照片 一个Photo
So if I have a photo, a photo star,
我可以将名字设为
I can actually set the name
照片拍照者的名字
of the photographer who took that photo.
我这里使用的不过是常规的点符号
So I'm just using dot notations and normal dot notation,
只是Photographer实现name
it's just that photographer implements name
Photo实现whoTook 而whoTook是一个Photographer
and photo implements who took and who took is a photographer,
因此有photo.whoTook.name
therefore, photo dot who took dot name.
有问题
Question?
问题是
Alright, so the question is
如果photo.whoTook为nil
would it auto create, if, if photo dot who took was nil,
它是否会自动在数据库中创建一个拍照者
would it automatically create a photographer in the database,
这样它就可以说.name=什么
so that it can say dot name equals whatever.
答案是否定的
And the answer is no.
这是普通的属性
This is normal properties.
如果photo.whoTook为nil
If photo dot who took is nil,
那么setName将会被发送给nil 什么都不做
then the set name will just be sent to nil, it will do nothing.
唯一在数据库中获得东西的方法是
So the only way to get things in the database is
前面我们看到的insertNewObjectForEntityForName
insert for entity for name, the thing we saw above there,
insert new object for entity for name,
不会自动创建[声音不清]
okay, it doesn't auto create the [inaudible].
好 这就是我访问属性的做法
Okay. So that's how I access my attributes.
如果我想在照片和拍照者类中添加代码又该怎样呢
What if I, though, wanted to add code to my photo or my photographer classes?
我可以把代码放到Photo.m和h中 不过这有个问题
I could put that code in photo dot m and h, but that would be a problem.
为什么呢
And why is that?
出问题的原因在于… 首先 为什么我要这样做
Well, that might be a problem because, well, first of all, why would I want to do that?
假设我想加一个class方法到Photo
Let's say I wanted to add a class method to photo
将Flickr数据库 Flickr字典作为参数
that took a Flickr database, a Flickr dictionary as an argument
在数据库中创建一张照片
and created a photo in, in the database,
这在Photo中将是一个很便利的工具方法
that would be an awfully convenient utility method to have in photo,
我可以说 开方括号 Photo
right, I could open square bracket photo,
在这个context下用这个Flickr数据创建一张照片
make a photo with this Flickr data, in a context,
它会这样做 这很酷
and it could do it, right, so that would be cool.
或者 假设我想导出一个属性
Or if I want to derive a property, like,
我有这个很好的属性thumbnailURL
I've got this nice property thumbnail URL,
但很不幸 它是一个字符串
but unfortunately it's a string, what if I wanted
如果我想要一个实际的UIImage缩略图呢
to have a UI image which was the thumbnail UI image,
这时我就可以在Photo中有一个方法
then I could have a little method in photo that just
只需要self.thumbnailURL 转为URL
self dot thumbnail URL, turn it into URL,
然后查一下 并不一定要是因特网
go look it up somewhere, preferably not on the internet,
或许吧 或许只是阻塞
but maybe, maybe it would just be a blocking,
一个进行阻塞的方法 我不知道
a method that would block, I don't know.
能够把这个加到Photo中也很酷 换句话说
So that would be cool to add to photo, as well, so in other words, it would be nice
如果我们能将照片相关的所有这些
if we could put all our photo-related stuff
放到Photo.m和h中
in photo dot m and h,
而不只是各种属性的setter和getter 那就好了
not just the setters and getters for all our properties.
为什么说这个存在问题呢 问题在于
Why this is a problem though, the problem is
在改变可视映射时
as you change your visual map,
你会不断调用重新生成方法
you're constantly calling that regenerate method,
菜单项 创建NSManagedObject
you know, menu item, the create NS-managed object,
这就总在重写它们
so it's called always rewriting them, okay,
其中的东西总会被破坏 因此我们不能这样做
it's always blasting what's in there, so we can't do it.
如果我们编辑了Photo.m和h 那么我们就不再能
If we edit photo m and h then we can no longer go
在Xcode中说 创建NSManagedObject的子类
into Xcode and say create NS managed object subclasses for me anymore,
这很不好
and that's a bummer.
因为 特别是在开发中 我们会迭代
Because, especially in development, we're iterating,
会添加属性 会添加实体
we're adding some properties, we're adding some entities,
改变关系 我们希望不断回头
changing some relationships, we want to constantly be going back
重新生成这些东西
and regenerating those things.
有问题吗
Question?
问题是 我能否设定默认值
Yeah, so, the question is could I set the default for the
让whoTook属性为Photographer alloc init
who took property to be photographer alloc init,
这样默认就总是创建一个新的拍摄者
basically, so the, the default would always default to creating a photographer
很不幸 这很酷 但你做不到
and unfortunately you can't do that, but that'd be cool.
默认都必须是我说的静态的 [声音不清]
The defaults all have to be kind of like I say, static, [inaudible].
我们要怎么做呢
Alright, so, what are we going to do then, because we want
我希望往Photo.m和h中添加方法
to add methods to photo dot m and h,
我们希望往Photographer.m和h中添加方法
and we want to add methods to photographer at m and h,
但我们又不想去碰这些文件
but we don't want to have to touch those files.
我们将用到到一个新的Objective-C语言特性
Well, we're going to use a new objective C language feature.
这是我要教你们的最后一个
The last one I'm going to teach you.
这之后你们都要掌握 它叫category(类别)
I think you know them all after this, called categories.
category让你能够添加方法到一个类
Categories, let's you add a method to a class
而无需创建它的子类
without sub classing it.
而且
And,
你甚至不需要有该类的源代码
you don't even have to have the source for that class that you're adding the method to.
有哪些例子呢
So what are some of examples of this?
在UIKit中 NSAttributedString有个方法
Well, in the UI kit, there's a method NS attributed string,
叫drawAtPoint
draw at point,
而NSAttributedString在Foundation中
well NS attributed string is in foundation,
它并不是UIKit的东西
it's not a UI kit thing,
它只是一个通用的带有属性的字符串
it's just a generic attributes on a string thing,
但UIKit添加了所有这些 drawAtPoint是一例
but UI kit adds all these, you know, draw at point,
它还定义了其它各种属性
and it defines all these other attributes that can be on there,
这都是在UIKit中进行的
and it does all that in UI kit,
这甚至不需要NSAttributedString的源代码
and it doesn't even need the source for NS attributed string.
只需要知道该类存在即可
It just needs to know that class exists.
NSIndexPath也一样
Same thing, NS index path.
我只说了NSIndexPath有两个方法
I told you NS index path only had two methods on it,
row和section
row and section,
实际上 NSIndexPath有很多方法
but actually NS index path has a whole bunch of methods on it,
它在Foundation中
it's in foundation,
它只是一个通用的索引指针
it's just a generic index pointer
指向任意的链表
into an arbitrary, you know, linked list of items,
只是UITableView希望调用row和section
it's just that UI table view wants to call it row and section,
于是它将row和section属性添加到NSIndexPath
so it adds the property's row and section to NS index path,
虽然UITableView在UIKit中
even though, again, table view is in UI kit,
但NSIndexPath却在Foundation中 框架都不一样
NS index path is in foundation, not even the same framework.
这是如何工作的呢
So, how does this work?
它是这样的
And it looks like this.
你有一个接口和实现
You have an interface and implementation,
就像类 不过你这里说的不是
just like the class, but you say, instead of saying
@interface 类名 冒号 超类
at sign interface, name of class, colon, superclass,
而是@interface 要添加方法的类名
you say at sign interface, the name of the class I want to add methods to,
这里括号中就是category的名称
and then in parentheses, what I'm going to call this category,
任何名字都行
and you can call it anything you want.
我叫它AddOn 你也可以叫它Flickr
So here I've called it add on, but you could call it Flickr,
或是Create 什么都行
you could call it Create, whatever you wanted to do.
然后你只需要列出你想添加的所有方法
And then you just list all the methods you want to add to this class,
也可以是属性
and they can be properties,
这里我有只读属性 还有另外一个方法
here I have a read-only property and another method.
把这些东西添加到这里之后 @end收尾
You just add, put them on there, and then at sign end.
你只需要做这些
So that's all you need to do.
想要调用这些方法的人只需要
Now anyone who wants to call these methods just has
导入这个的头文件
to import this header file that has this in there.
不过 category有一个很大的局限
Now, there's a big restriction on categories,
巨大的局限 你不能使用实例变量
gigantic restriction, you can't use any instance variables.
你的方法的实现
So the implementation of your methods
不能使用任何实例变量 或是任何存储数据
cannot use any instance variables, or any stored data at all.
有办法绕过 不过这都是非法的
There are ways kind of around it, but they're hacks.
一般而言 category只适用于方法
So generally, categories is for methods,
没有状态 这有什么好的
they have no state, well what good is that?
你添加方法的对象本身 它有很多状态
Well, the object that you're adding the methods to, it has a lot of state
因此 这些方法的显现
and so these methods would be all implemented
都可以使用针对对象的状态
by using the state of the object you're adding the methods to.
让我们看看这两个方法的例子
So, like let's look at an example for these two methods.
这是实现 @implementation
So here's the implementation, the at sign implementation
Photo 照片 AddOn category
of photo, photos add on category,
我把这两个方法加到Photo类
so I'm adding these two methods to the photo class,
这是我们在Xcode中生成的类
which is that thing we generated in Xcode,
图像
image,
注意 这里只用了self.photoURL
you see it just uses self dot photo URL,
self是照片
self, is the photo,
因为这些方法被加到了Photo类
because these methods are being added to photo class.
因此self是照片
So, self is a photo,
.photoURL能获取属性 获取数据
dot photo URL gets that attribute, gets that, that data.
也许 这里实际上应该是
That's probably, it actually probably would be self,
来自字符串的NSURL
it would NS URL from string,
self.photoURL字符串
self dot photo URL string,
因为我们无法直接将URL放到数据库中
because we can't put URL's directly in the database,
无论如何 然后我们说return
but anyway, and then it would say return
UIImage imageWithData 返回图像
UI image, image with data, and return the image.
这里没有实例变量
So no instance variables there,
isOld也一样
it's not using any [inaudible], same thing with is old,
它可以说self.uploadDate timeIntervalSinceNow
it might say self dot upload date, time interval since now
大于一天时间
is greater than a day ago.
有问题
Question?
不 我是说 你不能声明任何新的
No I mean you cannot declare any new ones.
这里不能使用任何实例变量
So you cannot use any instance variables here,
你只能用类中的实例变量
you could only use instance variables in the class,
如果你要用类的 你必须通过属性等让其为公共
you're adding a two if they make them public, via properties or whatever.
category不能有任何实例变量 句号
Okay. You can't have any instance variables in a category, period.
你不能声明任何一个
Okay, you cannot declare any.
如果你想使用你要添加方法的类的实例变量
If you want to use instance variables
of the class you're adding the methods to,
这些变量必须是公共的
then they have to be public
因为你只能看到公共头文件
because all you can do is see the public header file,
你看不到Photo的实现
you don't see the implementation of photo,
加这些方法时你是盲的
you're adding these methods to it blind,
你对这些实现一无所知
you don't know anything about its implementation.
总之 这就是category
So anyway, so this is called categories,
我没有很早就讲这个 因为它很容易被滥用
I don't teach this to you early on because this is easily abused, alright?
你可以为UIKit类添加方法 你没有理由不可以
You could add methods to UI kit classes, there's no reason you couldn't.
你可以Foundation类添加方法
You could add methods to, you know, foundation classes,
完全不受限
completely unrestricted.
只是这样做的时候
The only thing is when you start doing that,
你的代码会变得有些模糊不清
you're code can kind of get a little obfuscated,
人们会说 什么 我不知道
people are like what, I didn't know that, you know,
这个UIKit类有这个方法
this UI kit class had that method,
因为这是你在category中加的
and it's because you've added it as a category over here
这会变得很难理解
and so it's just kind of hard to understand,
不过有时像这样 我们希望这样做 原因在于
but sometimes like this, we want to do that because it kind
它能将代码汇集在一起 让其看起来很好
of it, it collects our code and it makes things look nicer.
有问题
Question?
问题是 我能否重写
So the question is can I override or overwrite,
一个已经存在的方法
really, a method that already exists?
答案是 不要这样做
And the answer is don't do that.
这会很难理解
That is really hard to understand
读你代码的人会摸不着头脑
for people reading your code, what you mean by that.
只添加方法 不要尝试替换或是按别的方式
So only add methods, don't try to replace or otherwise,
使用相同方法
you know, use the same method.
问得很好
That's a good question.
好 这里有一个很常见的category方法
Alright, so, here's a common category method
我们经常会给NSManagedObject的子类添加
we add for subclasses of NS-managed object,
也就是创建
which is creation. So,
假设我有这个category 叫作Photo (Create)
imagine I had this category called photo create,
这是我要添加的方法
and I'm going to have this method that I'm going to add
Photo在ManagedObjectContext
to photo called photo with Flickr data
调用photoWithFlickrData
in managed object context,
它会查询数据库 看这张照片是否存在
and it's going to query that database, see if that photo already exists,
如果存在就将它返回 如果不存在
it's going to return it if it does, if not,
就insertNewObjectForEntityForName
it's going to insert new object for entity for name,
从你发送的字典初始化照片
initialize the photo from the dictionary you sent,
等等等 这一个方法会做所有这些工作
etc. etc. etc. It's going to do all the work, all in one method.
如果有人想用Flickr数据创建一张新照片
So that if someone wants to create a new photo using Flickr data,
他可以调用这个方法 Photo中的类方法
they can just call this one method, class method in photo.
这就是我们这样做的经典原因
So this is a classic reason why we would do this.
如何创建一个category呢
So, how do we create a category.
我们到Objective-C 当然是新文件了
So we go to objective C, new file, of course,
这里我们要的不是这里的Objective-C类
and instead of saying objective C class, right, you see objective C class there,
而是Objective-C category
you say objective C category,
这里Xcode不会问你要类和超类
and instead of asking you the class and the super class,
它只会问你 你想把它添加到什么类去
it's going to say what class do you want to add a method to
以及category取什么名称
and what do you want to call this category.
我要给Photo添加方法
So I'm going to add methods to photo,
而category名叫Flickr
and I'm going to call the category Flickr.
这时 它创建了Photo+Flickr.h
And then it creates photo plus Flickr dot h
和Photo+Flickr.m
and photo plus Flickr dot m.
这是category的标准命名惯例
Now, this is kind of the standard naming convention, for a category.
要加方法的类名+category名
You call it name of the class you're adding the methods to plus the name of the category.
+表示分隔符
Okay, the plus as a separator,
同时也表示你要加这些方法
and also because plus means you're adding these methods to it.
这是命名惯例
So it's kind of a naming convention.
这些头文件
You could call those header file
以及实现文件 其实你叫什么都可以
and the implementation file anything you want, really,
不过我们100%都会这么叫
but this is what we one hundred percent of the time call it.
类名+category名
Name of class, plus category.
可以看到 它创建了一个.h和一个.m文件
And you can see that it's created a dot h for me and a dot m,
我将我要加的方法放到.h中
and I just put the methods I want to add in the dot h
然后在.m中实现它们
and then I implement them in the dot m,
只不过我不能有任何实例变量 很遗憾
it's just that I can't, unfortunately, have any instance variables.
有问题
Yeah, question.
问题是 如果不是使用新文件 category
Yeah, so the question is instead of using new file, category,
而是创建一个空文件 直接键入这些东西
if I just created an empty file and started typing this stuff in,
Objective-C如何知道这是一个category
how does objective C know this is a category, well, the,
到新文件中找category
when you go new file in category,
其实只是为你提供了一种便利
that's just a convenience, it's just creating this for you as a convenience.
你显然可以直接键入
You could certainly just type this stuff in,
Objective-C认得它是category
it knows it's a category because it's
因为有@interface Photo (Flickr)
at sign interface photo, parentheses Flickr, right,
它认识这个括号
it knows that that parentheses thing,
有@符号 又有括号中的某个名称
if you have at sign parentheses with some word in there,
它就知道这是category
it knows that means a category,
在实现端也是一样 它能认出
and then same thing on the implementation side, you say okay,
我提供的是该category的实现
I'm providing implementation of that category.
答案是 你可以直接键入
So the answer is yeah, you can do that,
新文件只是为你提供一点便利 仅此而已
new file is just making it easy for you so it does this, that's all.
这方面还有问题吗
Okay, any question about this?
周三的演示上我们会看到这个
And we'll see this in the demo on Wednesday
我们会为Photo加一个category
where it will add a category, to photo.
好 现在你知道了如何插入对象 如何改变其属性
Okay. So now you know how to insert an object, you know how to change their properties.
如何创建自定义子类 这些都可以用点符号
We know how to create the custom subclass, so we can do all this with dot notation,
那从数据库中删除对象呢
what about deleting objects from the database.
这太简单不过了 就像黑武士喜欢说的 太容易了
This is all too easy, okay, as Darth Vader would say, all too easy.
你只需要在context上调用deleteObject
You just call delete object on the context, give the object,
删除就完成了
bam, it deletes it.
不过 删除对象还会有分支
Now, deleting the object can have ramifications.
删除一个拍照者 whoTook会被设为nil
You delete a photographer, it's going to set that who took to nil.
假设你没有选cascade式删除规则
Assuming you don't do that cascade delete rule
这时它会直接删掉拍照者
in which case it would delete the photographer, but, okay,
反正 删除会有分支
so deleting, you know, has ramifications,
你需要知道你在删什么 这很简单
you got to know what you're doing and deleting, it's very easy to do.
关于这个考虑两点
Two things to think about this.
一 记住 它并不实际删除照片
One, remember it doesn't actually delete the photo
或者说删除对象 在保存之前
or delete the object until you save,
自动保存后 删除才会发生
so the auto save comes around and it'll be deleted.
这是很简单很明显的一点
That's just a minor point, it's kind of obvious.
你做的所有修改也一样
Same thing with all the changes you make,
在自动保存或是你手动保存之前
that they don't happen on the database until that auto save happens,
它们并不发生在数据库上
or until you explicitly save.
关于删除的第二点
But the second thing with deletion,
你需要非常小心 看到参数photo了吗
you got to be really careful is, see that argument photo?
deleteObject:photo
Delete object colon photo?
如果这个photo由一个指针强引用
If that photo is a strongly-held to a pointer,
你最好在这之后将其设为nil
you better set it to nil right after this.
因为你无法再访问这个photo 它已经失效
Because you cannot access that photo anymore, it is invalid.
删除照片后 或者说删除对象之后
After you hit delete photo, or delete object rather,
记得删除掉所有指向它的强指针
that thing you deleted, get rid of all your strong pointers to it,
因为这不好
because it's no good.
它已经被删除了
It's been deleted.
如果下一行你又说photo.title=什么
So if you tried to say photo dot title equals something on the next line,
肯定会出现很糟糕的情况 别这样做
I don't even know what would happen, something bad, don't do it.
这非常明显 对吧
I mean, that's completely obvious, right?
但总有人忘记 结果发现程序又出问题了
But, it's something people forget and then they're like, wow, it's not working.
删除有一点很酷
One of the things about deletion that's kind of cool.
Core Data会发送方法
Core data will send the method,
发生消息 prepareForDeletion 给所有对象
send a message, prepare for deletion to all objects
当你发送deleteObject时
when you send delete object.
如果我说deleteObject:photo 这个photo会被发送
So if I say delete object photo, that photo will be sent,
如果它实现它 prepareForDeletion
if it implements it, prepare for deletion.
很酷的是
And the cool thing is,
你可以把这个prepareForDeletion放到一个category中
you can put this prepare for deletion in a category.
你可以在一个category中 把prepareForDeletion方法
So you can add the prepare for deletion method to photo,
加给Photo或是Photographer
or photographer, in a category.
prepareForDeletion中你打算做什么呢
Now what would you do in that prepare for deletion, well,
你不需要对whoTook或是photos做任何事情
you don't need to do anything with the who took or the photos
这些都帮你处理了
or anything that, that's all taken care of you for you,
但如果数据库中某处有另一个属性呢
but what if you had another property somewhere in the database,
它在为photos计数 诸如此类
which was counting the photos, or something like that,
删除某张照片会改变计数值
and deleting this photo would change that count,
为什么要有这种东西
and why would you have such a thing?
因为你有可能要查询照片计数
Because it's possible to just query the counted photos,
例如一个拍照者拍了多少
that a photographer has, for example.
也许 计数是出于效率考虑
Maybe, you know, it's your, its account, for efficiency,
你检查照片信息 跟踪计数
you're checking something about the photo and keeping this count.
在删除照片后 你或许应当更新计数
And maybe if you delete the photo you need to update that count.
所有这些 都可以在prepareForDeletion中做到
Well you can do that, all that kind of stuff here and prepare for deletion.
在prepareForDeletion中
You can basically do anything in the database
你可以做任何数据库中你想做的事
you want in prepare for deletion,
而要删除的东西还没被删除
and the thing that's being deleted is not yet deleted.
这个调用时 它还在数据库中
So it's still it the database that this is called.
但在从这个方法返回后 对象就会被删除
But after you return from this method, then the object's going to be deleted,
你最好是按需求更新了数据库
so you have better have updated the database however you need.
明白了吗
Got that?
好 你可以插入创建对象
Alright. So, now you can create objects with insert,
获取和设置属性 删除对象
you can get and set the properties, you can delete the objects.
数据库中还有最后一点 query(查询)
One last thing to want to do in a database, query, okay,
也就是到数据库中获取匹配标准的所有对象
which means go out into the database and get me objects that match some criteria.
Core Data中可以通过一种对象做到这个
So, we do this, in core data,
也就是NSFetchRequest(取回请求)
with an object called NS fetch request.
顾名思义 很好理解
It's exactly what you think it is,
你提出请求 从数据库中取回一些对象
you're requesting to fetch some objects from the database.
你需要四个要素来得到NSFetchRequest
You need four things to make an NS fetch request.
要取回的实体 这个很有趣
The entity to fetch, and this is an interesting one
因为在数据库中去取时 你只能取回…
because when you fetch from the database, you can only fetch,
在你执行它时 它会返回一个对象数组
fetch, when you execute it, it returns an array of objects,
一个NSManagedObject数组
an array of NS-managed objects,
或是其子类的数组 很好理解
or subclasses thereof, as you might imagine.
这个数组都需要是相同类型的实体
That array all have to be the same type of entity.
你在数据库中取回的数组不可能
So there are no way to do a fetch in a database that gives you an array back,
一部分是Photo 一部分是Photographer
some of the things are photos and some are photographers.
要么都是Photo 要么都是Photographer
They all have to be photos, all have to be photographers.
你需要指定你要取回的实体
So you have to specify the entity that you're trying to fetch.
理解吗
Understand what I mean by that?
这是最重要的了
That's the most important thing, in fact, the,
实际上 要创建FetchRequest
the way you create the fetch request is by
就必须指定你要取回的是哪类实体
specifying what kind of entity you're trying to fetch.
然后可选地 你可以指定
Then you can specify, optionally,
你希望接收多少个对象
how many of those objects you're willing to accept
一批有多大
and how big a batch,
如果你要取的很多
if, if you're fetching a whole bunch of them,
你可以指定你一次取多少
you can specify how many to get at a time,
要知道 在取照片时
because it's not going to, if you say
如果匹配的有一万张
get me these photos and it matches 10,000,
你不可能将一万个都取出数据库 存到内存
it's not going to load 10,000 things out of the database and into memory.
它会给你一万个占位符
It's going to kind of give you 10,000 placeholders
然后一小批一小批地取回
and then it's going to fetch them in little batches,
你可以指定批大小 具体要看你怎么使用对象
and you can specify the batch size depending on how you're going to use the object,
如果你是使用信息 如果是在表格视图中显示
if you use the information, if you're displaying it in a table view,
你可以把批大小设得很小 例如10到20
well you can set the batch size real small, like 10 or 20, however many,
满足表格视图中一般滚动所需即可
you know, would scroll around on a table view.
一次一般只能看到10到20个 这时可以用小的批大小
We can only see, you know, 10 or 20 at a time, so you've got a small batch size.
你可以控制这个
So you control that.
SortDescriptor(排序描述器) 我们会讲到
Sort descriptors, which we're going to talk about,
也就是如何对结果排序
which is how to sort the results,
要知道 结果是一个数组 而不是集合
because the results are an array, not a set.
数组就必然有顺序
So the array means it's ordered,
你必须指定对象给回来的顺序
so you got to specify what order to give those objects back in.
然后最重要的是Predicate(谓词)
And then, most importantly, the predicate,
谓词是说 你想要哪些实体 哪些照片
and the predicate says which of those entities you want, which photos?
哪些拍照者
Which photographers?
我们来看看这四大要素
So let's look at these four things.
FetchRequest是这样的
Here's what a fetch request looks like.
用fetchRequestWithEntityName创建
You create it with fetch request with entity name,
这告诉你是从哪取回的
that tells you what you're fetching out of there,
然后你可以设置批大小 批限制
and then you can set things like the batch size and the batch limit,
这些都是request上的属性
they're just properties on the request,
然后sortDescriptors是一个SortDescriptor数组
and then the sort descriptors is an array of sort descriptors,
我们会谈到为什么这是数组
we'll talk about why that's an array.
然后谓词是NSPredicate
And then the predicate is, is NS predicate.
这就是创建一个FetchRequest的方式
So this is how you would set up a fetch request.
非常简单
Very simple.
你可以查NSFetchRequest 具体看批大小
So, you can look up in NS fetch request how batch size works,
批限制 具体我不打算讲
how fetch limits works, I'm not going to get into detail
毕竟时间有限
about that for time reasons,
不过我打算仔细考虑排序描述器和谓词
but I am going to focus on sort descriptors and predicate
因为这些很重要 这是排序描述器
because those are really important, so let's look at the sort descriptor.
创建排序描述器用这个类NSSortDescriptor
You create a sort descriptor using this class NS sort descriptor.
创建它有很多种类方法
And it has quite a number of class methods to create it,
你可以自己去文档查
so you should go look at the documentation and familiarize yourself,
不过一般都是形如sortDescriptorWithKey
but they're generally of the form sort descriptor with key,
这是排序所根据的键
so that's the key you want to sort by,
如果我要取照片
so if I were fetching for photos,
我可以让照片按标题排序
I want to get the result sorted by the title of the photo,
这是最典型的做法
that would be a classic thing.
ascending(升序)
Ascending is whether
YES是字母顺序 NO是反字母顺序
it's alphabetical order or reverse alphabetical order,
然后selector(选择器)很有趣
and then the selector is interesting there.
这个方法将被用于在排序过程中对比照片
That is the method that will be used to compare photos, while it's sorting them.
结果将会依标题排序
So, it's going to sort the results by the title,
它会用到这个方法
and it's going to be using the method here,
localizedStandardCompare
localized standard compare
来对比标题 以明确如何排序
to compare the titles to know how to sort them.
首先看 什么是localizedStandardCompare
Now, A, what is localized standard compare?
localizedStandardCompare是说
Localized standard compare means
像Mac finder中的方法一样排序
sort them like they would look in the Mac finder, basically.
或者说得更直白一些
Or, that's kind of colloquial way of saying it, but basically,
按照一般人认为应该的方法来排序
sort them how real people think things should be sorted,
对大小写不敏感
not case insensitively,
对发音符做出正确反应
do the right thing with diacritic marks,
如果语言中带有发音符 这类
if it's a language that has a lot of diacritics, that kind of thing.
这就是localizedStandardCompare
That's what localized standard compare is.
此外还有其它一些选择器可用
There are other selectors that are sensible
如果是字符串类型的属性
if it was a string type property,
例如localizedCaseInsensitiveCompare
like localized case insensitive compare,
听起来一样
which sounds the same,
大小写不敏感的排序
case insensitive sorting,
但这里 发音符的处理方式会不同
but the diacritics are handled differently in that case.
因此 你会希望使用标准对比
So that's why you would want to use standard compare.
你可以查阅SortDescriptor 看有哪些内建方法
So you can look up in sort descriptors, see what kind of methods are kind of built in.
除了字符串 别的也可以排序
If you were, you can sort by things besides strings,
例如你可以使用上传日期的排序描述器
you can say sort descriptor with key upload date,
这时选择器将是compare:
and then the selector would want to be compare colon.
compare:是大多数甚至所有…
Compare colon is a method most things, if not all,
或许除了NSData
except for NS data maybe,
数据库中的东西几乎都会对它作出响应
things in the database will respond to,
compare:可以说是默认对比
compare colon, it's kind of the default compare,
不过通常对于字符串 它并不是最好的
but it's not going to do what you want, usually with reverse string,
你希望用更好的
so you want a better one,
不过它对于日期和数字这些还是可以的
but it will work for dates and things like, and numbers, things like that.
这是选择器
So that's the selector.
创建SortDescriptor时 你可以不用选择器
You can leave that selector off, when you create the sort descriptor,
只说sortDescriptorWithKey和ascending
just say sort descriptor with key ascending,
闭方括号 你也会得到对比
close square bracket, and you'll get compare.
这时对比使用的是默认值
So, compare is kind of the default one you get.
为什么要给FetchRequest一个数组呢
Why do we give an array of these things to the fetch request?
我们看到request.sortDescriptors
Okay, when, we saw request dot sort descriptors,
这是一个描述器的数组
it was an array of these,
这是很久就有的姓名问题
well that's the old last name, first name thing.
我可能要取回一些人
If I said hey, I'm going to fetch some people,
从雇员数据库中取一些雇员 我要按姓排序
some employees out of an employee database, and I want you to sort it by last name.
显然 所有史密斯都排到了一起
Well, of course, all the Smith's would all sort to the same thing.
然后 你希望再对其名排序
So, you want to then sort those by the first name.
这就要两个排序描述器 一个按姓来
So you provide 2 sort descriptors, one that sorts by last name,
这是主要排序 然后根据名排序 这是次要排序
that's the primary sorting, and then one by first name is the secondary sorting.
另一个很常见的情况是表格视图 注意了
Another common one is a table view, pay attention,
因为作业中 你们需要考虑到这个
because your homework, you might have to do this, is
或许我的表格视图就像你们这次的作业一样
maybe I'm doing the table view like you're doing your current assignment,
我排序是地方的名字
and I'm sorting, you know, basically by the name of the place, in the place one,
不过我还要对section的国家进行排序
but I'm supposed to do it by countries, sections by country,
而且我应当首先对国家排序
so really I need to sort first by country,
然后才排序国家内的地名
then I sort by the name of the place in the country.
这就是使用两种排序描述器的例子
So, that's an example where you might use two sort descriptors.
国家排序 然后地方
Country sort then the place.
我让所有地名排好序 国家放前面
That's so that I can get them in order so that the, their by country first.
明白了吗
That make sense?
好 再看谓词 这非常核心
Alright, predicates, so this is the guts, this is the thing
它说的是 我要哪些照片 哪些拍照者
that says which photos do I want, which photographers do I want, and,
而且在创建时 NSPredicate和NSString很像
and NS predicate looks a lot like NS string when it comes to creating them.
就像NSString stringWithFormat
So just like we have NS string, string with format,
这里有NSPredicate predicateWithFormat
we actually have NS predicate, predicate with format.
你可以指定任意字符串
And you can specify this arbitrary string.
这是一把双刃剑
Now, this is good and bad.
好消息是 这非常灵活
The good news is this is incredibly flexible
你可以指定很多难以置信的标准
and you can specify unbelievable kinds of criteria
用于寻找数据库中的内容
for finding what things you want in the database.
坏消息是 你需要学一些东西
The bad thing is, it's a little bit for you to learn,
看起来就像你要学习一门语言
because it's almost like you have to learn a little bit of a language here,
谓词语言 关于如何指定你要选择的东西
the predicate language for how you specify what you want to choose.
基本格式让你能够进行%@符号替换
The basic format allows you to do the percent at sign replacement,
就像NSString中一样 例如这里
just like you could with NS string, so here, for example,
我在找所有来自flickr-5服务器的缩略图URL
I'm looking for all the thumbnail URLs that come off of Flickr five server.
于是我这里说 谓词是thumbnailURL 包含flickr-5
So I'm saying predicate is thumbnail URL contains Flickr five,
但这里没有直接写flickr-5
but I don't put the Flickr five right in there,
我使用%@符号 而且它是一个参数
I use percent at sign, and it's an argument.
我可以用%@来替换
So I can use percent at sign for replacement,
我不仅可以替换右侧 包含的对象
and I can replace not only the right side, what's contained,
我还可以替换左侧
but I can replace the left side,
例如我要搜索是否包含flickr-5的属性
like which property I want to search to see if it contains Flickr five.
等下我会讲到包含(contains) 有问题
And we'll talk about contains in a second, question?
对 问题是 这是不是
Correct. Yeah so, this is not just, the question is is
生成一个字符串然后传递
that just making a string and passing it off
答案是否定的
and the answer is no,
NSPredicate会看你在解析什么
NS predicate is actually looking at what you're parsing and,
不过 它不知道你正在什么数据库中进行取回
now it's, it can't know what database you're doing a fetch into,
因此 它只在取回时才会失败
so it won't be until fetch time that it might fail.
如果你说thumbnailFoo包含什么
If you say thumbnail foo, contains whatever,
你可以创建这个谓词
its predicate is going to let you create that predicate,
但在真正取回时
but then when you go to do the fetch it's going
你会被告知 本数据库中没有thumbnailFoo
to say no property thumbnail foo in this database.
好 你们看到这里有contains
Okay, so, you see this one's contained.
contains是说 一个字符串包含在另一个字符串之中
Contains means, you know, that string is contained in the other string,
顾名思义
exactly what you want,
contains是用于创建谓词的一点语言词汇
so contains is one of the words in this little language for setting up predicates.
这里还有很多别的例子
Here's a whole bunch of other examples.
今天我不可能把所有谓词都讲完
I'm not going to teach you all of predicate today, you're going
你们需要自己去查NSPredicate的文档
to have to look at NS predicate documentation,
不过这里有一些例子
see what it can do, but here's a bunch of examples.
显然 这里有等于
Obviously, you have equals,
你可以说uniqueId = %@
so you can say unique ID equals percent at sign,
或许是Flickr对象 Flickr照片 唯一ID
maybe the Flickr object, the Flickr photos, unique ID,
你可以说name contains[c]
you can say name contains with square bracket C,
这是说大小写不敏感地包含
that means contains case insensitively.
这是一种contains 你还可以有大于和小于
So that's part of the thing, you can have greater than and less than,
假设我有一个日期属性叫viewed(被阅览)
so if I had a date property called viewed,
我可以说 如果viewed大于特定日期
I could say if viewed is greater than a certain date,
例如今天的日期
like today's date, for example,
或许小于今天的日期会更合理
or, it would be, I guess, less than today's date
或是小于今天的日期减24小时 诸如此类
or less than today's date minus 24 hours, whatever,
你可以用大于或小于
so you can use greater than or less than.
你还可以用点符号来跟踪关系
You can use dot notation to follow relationships.
你可以说 whoTook.name = CS193P授课者
So you can say who took dot name equals CS193p instructor, right?
这里可以是一个查询 或者谓词
So you could have, this would be a query or a predicate
用于搜索照片 实体
for searching in the photos, entities,
你希望获得照片实体
so you're trying to get photos entities,
但是照片实体要求满足拍照者名字是某个人名
but you want photos entities where the who took name is some photographers name.
你所获得的东西是照片 但是查询
So, the things you're getting are photos, but the query,
用于找它们的谓词
the predicate you're using to find them,
却是用点符号考察拍照者名字
is looking over at the photographer using dot notation,
明白吗
you understand this?
要做好作业 理解这些是必须的
You definitely need to understand this for your homework.
你可以进行很强大的搜索
And you can do really powerful searches like
如 给我标题包含某内容的任何照片
give me any photo who's title contains,
抱歉 这里是 拍照者查询
sorry, give me, this would be a photographer query,
我要搜的是拍照者
so let's say I'm searching photographers,
给我照片标题包含这个的任何(any)拍照者
give me any photographer where any of its photos title contains this.
这个any就是这里所特有的
So that any is kind of a special thing,
意思是说 我要找拍照者
and that means I'm the photographer, look at all my,
在数据库中搜所有拍照者
look at, in the database at all the photographers,
看它们拍的照片的集合
look through their, their photos set,
看其中所有照片 看所有照片的标题
to look at all their photos, look at all the titles of all those photos,
看是否包含这个字符串
see if it contains this string,
如果包含 返回这个拍照者
and if it does, return that photographer.
你肯定会说 哇 这得消耗多少计算力啊
Now this seems, I'm sure you're like whoa, that is going to take
如果有成千上万的照片 成百上千的拍照者怎么办
a lot of computing power if I had thousands of photos and hundreds of photographers,
实际上 数据库能够很好地完成这个
but actually, databases know how to do this really, really well.
你所做的事情不过是
And all this stuff that you're doing is
生成SQL侧发生的东西
generating stuff that happens on the sequel side,
你会得到一个大的SQL语句生成在这里
so you're going to get a big sequel statement generated here
将表格结合在一起 进行搜索
to join these tables, do these searches,
这会非常高效
it's going to be incredibly efficient,
Core Data很重要的一点便是 它非常高效
and one thing to understand about core data is it's very efficient.
它生成的SQL最大程度地进行了优化
The sequel it generates is totally tuned to the max.
话虽如此
Having said that,
有些查询还是会比其它更高效
there are certain queries that are more efficient than others
虽然达成的目的都是一样的
that can accomplish the same goals.
如果你想成为Core Data专家 要创建大数据库
So, if you get to be a core data expert and you start building big databases
在大数据集上要进行很多工作量巨大的查询
and you're making a lot of big queries on big data sets,
你会最终了解 什么查询好
you will eventually learn what makes a good query,
什么查询不那么好
what makes a not so good query, etc.
但在作业中 你还不需要担心这些
For your homework, you don't have to worry about that yet.
首先只需打好基础
Let's get the basics first.
有问题
Question.
问题是不是
So the question, you mean like
大于和小于这些能否作为%@符号传入
the greater than and less than, can I pass that in as a percent sign?
你不能进行SQL…
Yes. You can't do sequel,
问题是 能否使用%@符号进行SQL隐码攻击
the question is can I do sequel injection by using the percent at sign to,
从而让运算符可配置
to basically make the operator be, you know,
答案是不能
configurable, and the answer is you can't do that.
NSPredicate会报错
NS predicate would complain about that.
NSPredicate知道什么时候%@符号在右侧
NS predicate does know when a percent at sign is a right-hand
什么时候在这些表达式左侧
or a left-hand of one of these expressions, so
答案是不 你不能那样做
the answer is no. You can't do that.
好 这里有一些例子 我只是给一些例子
Okay, so there's a bunch of examples, again, I'm just trying to give you the examples,
这里我不打算把所有谓词都讲一遍
we're not trying to teach you predicate here.
还有一个复合谓词
There's also a compound predicate.
在NSPredicate中 你可以说AND或OR
In the NS predicate, you can say and or or.
例如你可以说
So you could say
(name = %@) OR (title = %@)
name equals percent at sign or title equals percent at sign,
如果你的对象有一个name和一个title
okay, if you had an object that had a name and a title.
你也可以说
Or you could say
(whoTook.name=%@) OR (title=%@)
who took dot name equals blah, or title equals blah,
虽然没什么意义 但你可以这样做
it kind of wouldn't make much sense, but you could.
在代码中创建复合谓词还可以使用
You can also create compound predicates in code by doing,
NSCompoundPredicate中的and谓词或or谓词
using and predicate or or predicate in NS compound predicate.
它会取一个谓词的数组 形成复合谓词
And it just takes an array of other predicates and makes a compound one.
这就像是代码中if-then的and和or
That's like if you want the and-ing and or-ing to kind of be if then, okay, in code,
只是内建到字符串中
as opposed to just built into the string.
高级查询 出于时间考虑 我打算跳过这个
Advanced querying, for time reasons I'm going to skip this,
不过键值编码也就是
but key value coding, which is the thing
让你使用点符号在字典内往下搜索的东西
that lets you use dot notation to search down inside of a dictionary,
它是valueForKeyPath那些
it's the value for key path business.
你可以在数据库中使用valueForKeyPath
You can kind of do value for key path in the database,
我们没有讨论过这些
and there is, we didn't talk about this,
不过键值编码中有一点很酷
but there is a really cool thing in key value coding,
也就是函数 其中有个函数
which is functions, and one of the functions,
或许在你的作业中有用 注意了 是@count
which you probably will need for your homework, so pay attention, is at sign count.
如果你将@count放到你要查询的东西里面
So, if you put at sign count in the thing you're querying for,
只要它左侧是一个集合 一个NSSet
as long as the thing to the left of it is an array, or a set,
sorry, a set, one of these NS sets,
那它就会将它替换为集合中元素的计数值
then it will replace that with the count of how many things are in that set.
例如 如果我想找的所有拍照者
So, for example, if I wanted to find out all the photographers,
满足条件拍的照片多于五张
give me back all of the photographers who have taken more than five photos,
我的谓词将是photos.@count>5
my predicate would be photos dot at sign count is greater than five.
还有其它@ 例如@avg(平均值)等等
And there are other at signs, at sign average, at sign,
你可以自己去查有哪些 这里我给了个链接
you can look through and find out what there is, I put a link in here,
你们知道 我很少在幻灯片中给链接
you know I don't, I usually don't put links in my slides,
不过这个确实值得一看
but this one is worth looking at.
这个能对任何键值编码的东西奏效
And, this also works, it works for any key value coding things,
例如对字典
like for dictionaries, so
你可以回Shutterbug
go back to the shutter bug
尝试propertyListResults valueForKeyPath
and try doing property list results, value for key path,
photos.photo.@avg.latitude
photos dot photo dot average dot latitude.
有人试着答下 这个会返回什么吗
Anyone hazard what that returns?
请讲
Yeah?
对 它会返回所有照片的平均纬度值
Correct. It returns the average latitude of all the photos.
这是给你们留的 祝玩的开心
So, that's something for you to, to have fun with.
你还可以创建更复杂的表达式
You can build even more complicated expressions
有一个机制可以到数据库中查询
and there's a mechanism to query into the database
但不获得NSManagedObject
and not get back an array of NS-managed objects,
而获得对其中内容进行计算后得到的数据
but to actually get kind of data that's been calculated from,
这样做时 你得到的
from what's in there, and when you do that,
将不是NSManagedObject数组 而是NSDictionary数组
instead of getting an array of NS-managed objects, you get an array of NS dictionaries,
这些字典包含键和值 这正是你要找的数据
and those dictionaries contain keys and values, which is the data you look for.
这些都是高级内容 看到标题了吗 高级查询
This is all super advanced, see the title of this thing, advanced querying,
我不打算在课上细讲
not going to talk about it in this class,
我只是想让你们知道 FetchRequest可以被用于
but just so you know, that fetch request can be used to create something
实际取回数据 而不是取回ManagedObject
that's actually fetching data rather than just fetching managed objects.
好 我们把所有这些为request综合起来
Alright. So, let's put it all together for the request.
这是一个request
So I created, this is a request.
请求所有拍照者
That's going to get all the photographers,
代码是fetchRequestWithEntityName Photographer
so I say fetch request fetchRequestWithEntityName photographer,
请求过去24小时内拍过照的
who have taken a photo in the last 24 hours,
昨天 这需要NSDate
so I get yesterday, which is NS date,
dateWithTimeIntervalSinceNow -24小时
date with time interval since now minus 24 hours.
谓词 any photos.uploadDate > 某某
Predicate, any photos dot upload date greater than whatever.
昨天
Yesterday.
然后 我要按拍照者名字排序
And then I'm going to sort it by the photographer's name,
一个SortDescriptor的数组 按名字排序
so an array of one sort descriptor, where the sort descriptor's the name,
这里会用compare
it's going to be using compare here,
这可能不好
which is probably not good, I probably
或许@selector(localizedStandardCompare:)会更好
want to say selector at sign localized compare.
这就是创建request的方式
So that's I would create a request.
有了request后 如何执行呢
Now that I have a request, how do I execute it?
答案是
And the answer is
我们使用NSManagedObjectContext中的
we use the method execute fetch request
executeFetchRequest方法
in NS-managed object context.
NSManagedObjectContext是一切的中心
So I told you NS manage object context is the hub of everything
也是查询的中心
and it's the hub of querying, as well.
可以看到 它有一个额外的参数
And you can see it has a little extra argument there,
error:&error 这会返回NSError
error colon, at sign error, which will return an NS error
发生错误时 这会告诉你错误在哪
and tell you what went wrong if things went wrong,
如果executeFetchRequest返回nil 你能知道出错了
and you can tell things went wrong with the fetch request
这是使用FetchRequest时的情况
if execute fetch request returns nil.
如果executeFetchRequest返回nil 那就肯定出错了
If execute fetch request returns nil, something went wrong,
&error会填入某种错误
and that at sign error will be filled out with some error.
如果返回的是空数组 不是nil
If it returns an empty array, that's not nil,
而是空数组
empty array,
这意味着 没有匹配请求的内容
that means nothing matches what you're requesting.
没有错误
So no error.
只是你请求的对象没有 它们都不匹配你的谓词
It's just that you requested objects and there aren't any that match that predicate.
否则 它会返回一个NSManagedObject数组
Otherwise, it's going to return an array of NS-managed objects.
或是其子类 Photo
Or, subclasses thereof, photos stars,
Photographer * 这些你所设置的实体名
photographer stars, whatever you set as the entity name,
它会传回这些组成的数组
it's going to pass an array of them.
就这了
That's it.
查询不能再简单了
It could not be simpler to query.
查询结果有一点我想提下
One thing about the query results, by the way,
如果你想找一万个东西 你不会得到一万个东西
if you query 10,000 things, you're not going to get 10,000 things,
你会得到一万个占位符
you're going to get 10,000 placeholders
在你开始看属性时
and as you start looking at the attributes,
你才会从数据库中获得它们
then it'll start faulting them in from the database.
这里隐藏有很多性能优化方面的内容
So there's a lot of performance optimization going on behind the scenes
你现在并不需要知道
that you don't really need to know about,
但获取会发生
but faulting is happening,
有些专注数据库的人 可能对此感到担忧
for those of you who are database heads and you're probably worried about this,
别担心 并非所有数据都从表格中取出了
no worries, it's not actually pulling all that data out of those tables,
在访问过程中 你能获得它们
it faults them in as you access them.
简单讲下Core Data线程安全
Quick thing about core data thread safety.
NSManagedObjectContext并不线程安全 换言之
NS-managed object is not thread safe, in other words,
你不能简单在多线程中用它
you can't just use it in multiple threads,
不过你可以安全访问它们
but you can safely access them.
大多数ManagedObject
Most managed objects,
创建时都用了线程包含
we create them with this kind of thread containment,
线程并发机制
thread concurrency mechanism.
NSManagedObjectContext中有一个方法
There's a method in NS-managed object context,
你会希望用到 叫performBlock
which you will want to use, called perform block,
它没有参数 而是取一段代码
it just takes a block with no arguments.
任何你希望对context做的事 插入对象 查询等等
Anything you want to do on a context, inserting objects, querying, anything,
都可以在performBlock中执行
do it inside a perform block.
为什么这样做呢
Why do you do that?
它会对context在安全队列中执行
It'll do it on the safe queue for that context,
这就确保了线程安全
and it'll guaranteed to be safe, thread safe.
这个安全队列有可能是主队列
Now, that safe queue might be the main queue,
因此 这并不一定能让你拥有多线程
so this will not necessarily give you multithreaded.
但它会很安全 请养成这样做的习惯
But it will be safe, so get in the habit of doing this,
或许以后哪一天
because if you do come, come to a day
你就会使用NSManagedObjectContext
when you're using NS-managed object context
并在不同队列上创建它们
and you're creating them on different queues,
你可以在一个队列载入一个数据库
so you can load the database in one queue
同时在另一个队列中查看
while you look at another, whatever,
这都是可行的
which is all doable,
你需要这个performBlock 至少这样做没有坏处
you need to be doing this perform block, it doesn't hurt to do it,
我建议你们养成习惯这样做
so might as well do it.
父上下文我没时间讲
And parent context I don't have time to talk about.
实际上 Core Data还有很多东西我都没时间讲
There is a ton other stuff, actually, in core data I don't have time to talk about
因为今天的课就快完了
because we're at the end of lecture today.
乐观锁
Optimistic locking,
回滚未保存状态变化 这很好理解
rolling back unsaved changes to, you know, states that make sense,
撤销和重做我讲过
undo and redo I talked about.
不刷新时间 也就是取回后数据要待多长时间
Staleness, you do a fetch and it sits around for a long time,
而不被刷新
the data could be stale,
一定时间后 需要重新取回
it might need to be refetched, thrown out and refetched.
这里有很多东西 我都讲不了
It just, a massive amount of stuff, can't talk about it.
从这里 你需要熟练掌握
When you walk out of here, what you really want to be comfortable with is you know how
如何创建可视映射 插入对象 创建子类
to create the visual map, insert objects, make the subclasses,
使用点符号来访问 删除对象 查询对象
use dot notation to access them, delete objects, and query for them.
这就是Core Data基础 这就是我们今天的内容
Okay, that's the fundamentals of core data, that's what we talked about today,
这就是你们需要从这门课中学到的
that's what you should, need to know how to do for this class.
此外 你只需要知道还有很多内容
And then outside of that, you just need to know that there's a lot more,
如果你要严肃了解数据库方面
and if you're going to do serious database work,
这些都需要你自己去读
you need to some reading up on that.
好 就这些了
Okay, so that's it.
很抱歉我拖了几分钟堂 周三再见
Sorry to keep you a couple minutes over and I will see you on Wednesday
到时会有一个大的演示
with a big demo of all this stuff.
更多内容 请访问我校官网stanford.edu
> For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.